<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A right frutefull and approoued treatise, for the artificiall cure of that malady called in Latin Struma, and in English, the evill, cured by kinges and queenes of England Very necessary for all young practizers of chyrurgery. Written by William Clowes, one of her Maiesties chyrurgions, in the yeare of our Lord. 1602.</title>
            <author>Clowes, William, ca. 1540-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840755</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840755</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5284</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5284)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 879:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A right frutefull and approoued treatise, for the artificiall cure of that malady called in Latin Struma, and in English, the evill, cured by kinges and queenes of England Very necessary for all young practizers of chyrurgery. Written by William Clowes, one of her Maiesties chyrurgions, in the yeare of our Lord. 1602.</title>
                  <author>Clowes, William, ca. 1540-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 68, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde [and are now to bee solde at Master Laybournes, a barber chirurgian dwelling vpon Saint Mary-Hill, neere Billings-gate],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from K3v.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The artificiall cure of the struma.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scrofula --  Treatment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> FRVTEF<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> AND APPRO<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Treatiſe, for the Artifici<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>that Malady called in Latin <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in Engliſh, the <hi>Evill,</hi> cured by <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Queenes of England</p>
            <p>Very neceſſary for all youn <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Chyrurgery.</p>
            <p>Written by WILLIAM CLOWES <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chyrurgions, in the yeare <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Allde. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſidered with my ſelfe (curteous and friendly Reader) the graue &amp; wiſe ſaying of <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> that Honour maintaineth Artes, wherby men are greatly addicted to ſtudy: So, as it is ſaid, if a man looke into the courſe of this world, and into humaine affayres, yee ſhall finde that ſuch Artes as ſerue the peoples neceſsity, &amp; haue their neceſſarie vſe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, haue been greatly eſteemed, and the Profeſſors thereof highly rewarded. Amongſt a number of which lawdable Artes &amp; Sciences, let vs make our conſideration of Chirurgery, the maintain<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and reſtorer of our healthes: For it is a moſt true receiued opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt worthy writers, that Chirurgery is (indeede) an ancient part of Phiſicke, as it appeareth by <hi>Iaques Guillemeau</hi> of <hi>Orleans</hi> ordinary Chirurgian to the now French King: who auoucheth, that before Phiſick was inuented, created, or found out, Chirurgery was practized, and ſufficiently knowne in al places: as it appeareth (ſaith he) by the teſtimonie of <hi>Homer,</hi> in the ſecond booke of his <hi>Ilyades:</hi> who wrote the valiant enterpriſes, and trauels of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> as did <hi>T<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Liuius,</hi> the worthy actes and monuments of the Ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.</hi> Moreouer, it is ſaid, that <hi>Apollo</hi> for his skill, and <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> his ſonne, were honoured (as Gods) of al the worthy <hi>Grecians, Podalerius</hi> and <hi>Machaon</hi> the two ſonnes of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> were held in great honour &amp; reputation, at the ſiedge of <hi>Troy,</hi> vnder <hi>A game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> Captaine of the <hi>Grecians.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon of all ages, was highly eſteemed by the <hi>Athenians: Eraſiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> of Noble <hi>Saleucus: Diocles,</hi> of <hi>Antigonus: Oribaſius, <hi>Iulian: Dioſcorides,</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> who followed the warres ouer <hi>Aegipt, Parthia, Armenia, Perſia, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> and <hi>Siria:</hi> and all to augment and encreaſe their knowledge &amp; skill. Laſt of all the ſaid Worthyes, I heere nominate <hi>Gallen,</hi> who is called the light of all good learning: and hee alſo was greatly honoured of <hi>Traian</hi> the Emperour, and he followed the warres with
<pb facs="tcp:5284:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Europa:</hi> I had heere likewiſe thought good to haue ſpoken ſomewhat of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> but I muſt conſeſse his Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine hath a more pregnant ſence, then my wit or reach is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue: onely this I can ſay by experience, that I haue practiſed certaine of his inuentions Chirurgicall, the which I haue found to be ſingular good, &amp; worthy of great commendations. How be it, much ſtrife I know there is betwen the <hi>Galeniſtes</hi> and the <hi>Paracelſians,</hi> as was in times paſt betweene <hi>Aiax</hi> and <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> for <hi>Achilles</hi> Armour. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, for my part I will heere ſet vp my reſt &amp; contentation, how impertinent and vnſeemely ſo euer it make ſhew: That is to ſay, if I finde (eyther by reaſon or experience) any thing that may be to the good of the Patients, and better increaſe of my knowledge &amp; skil in the Arte of Chirurgery, be it eyther in <hi>Galen</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus;</hi> yea, <hi>Turke, Iewe,</hi> or any other Infidell: I will not refuſe it, but be thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God for the ſame. How be it, I will in no wiſe meddle with their Infidelity, though I imbrace their knowledge and skill in humane verityes and inuentions, be it eyther in Phiſicke or Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, or any of the other laudable Sciences. Now I will diſcourſe no further, vntill a more fit opportunity be offered: But very briefly I meane heere to demonſtrate and deliuer vnto the friendly Reader, the cure of a certaine vnnaturall tumor or abſceſse, called in Latin, <hi>Struma:</hi> of the <hi>Arabians, Steophala:</hi> but generally, in Engliſh, it is called, <hi>the Kings or Queenes Euill:</hi> A diſeaſe repugnant to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which grieuous malady is knowne to be miraculouſly cured &amp; healed, by the ſacred hands of the Queenes moſt Royall Maieſty, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by Diuine inſpiration and wonderfull worke and power of God, aboue mans skill, Arte and expectation: Through whoſe Princely Clemency, a mighty number of her Maieſtyes moſt Loyall ſubiects, and alſo many ſtrangers borne, are dayly cured and healed, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would most miſerably haue periſhed. For many of them (their pouerty was ſuch) were not able to pay but a very little or nothing at all for their cure. And ſo I heere conclude, that as God by his diuine giftes, doth cure this <hi>Strumous</hi> Malady: ſo alſo of his great goodnes, he doth giue Artificiall giftes, for the curing of the ſaid Infirmity. But whereas Artificiall giftes doe many times fayle thee, doe his deuine giftes take place &amp; reuaile: as after more at large ſhall appeare.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>William Clowes,</hi> one of her Maieſties Chirurgions.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:3"/>
            <head>Tho: Bonhami, in Medic: Doct. Exaſtichon: In laudem Authoris.</head>
            <l>CLVSIVS es dictus, meliús ſed APERTIVS eſses:</l>
            <l>Clauſa aperîs, alios quae latuêre prius,</l>
            <l>Regaliſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> mali cauſam, auxiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> RECLVDENS,</l>
            <l>Doctus Apollineae porrigis artis opem.</l>
            <l>Multi Aſclepiadae fruſtra hanc petiêre coronam,</l>
            <l>Solus habê, palmam hanc tradit Apollo tibi.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:4"/>
            <head>Gent. in commendation of William Clowes his booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BY long experience and by practiſe great,</l>
               <l>Time hath affoorded to this painfull man</l>
               <l>A helpfull cure, which heeretofore to treate,</l>
               <l>The greateſt Clarkes haue doubted how &amp; whan.</l>
               <l>To cure the ſame giue <hi>Clowes</hi> due praiſe therefore,</l>
               <l>That hath performed this and many more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet conceiue, this is not <hi>Clowes</hi> his cure,</l>
               <l>Our Soueraigne Lady, and his Miſtris Queene:</l>
               <l>Seemes well content her man may put in vre</l>
               <l>So much as ſhe affoordes; as may be ſeene</l>
               <l>By <hi>Clowes</hi> his ſcope, the reſt ſhe challengeth,</l>
               <l>As Queene annoynted and by Royall birth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then Phiſicke yeeld; giue place Chirurgery;</l>
               <l>The Rationall and Practicke for this paine</l>
               <l>Are both a like: her Peereleſſe Maieſtie</l>
               <l>Healeth by God alone, Arte is but vaine.</l>
               <l>This ſhe performes, to write I muſt ſurceſſe,</l>
               <l>Her hidden skill no pen can well expreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How much then are we to the high God bound,</l>
               <l>For ſending vs this Princeſſe heere on earth?</l>
               <l>Within whoſe breſt, ſuch helpes are dayly found,</l>
               <l>As heales her ſubiectes at the point of death.</l>
               <l>She cures, ſhe cares, ſhe ſaues vs all by skill:</l>
               <l>She hurteth none, but helpes with louing will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Liue, liue for aye: what humour leadeth me?</l>
               <l>I gan to write in <hi>VVilliam Clowes</hi> his praiſe;</l>
               <l>Her onely name hath drawne my quill I ſee.</l>
               <l>And daunted ſo my ſence by ſundry waies:</l>
               <l>That like as <hi>Zenxis</hi> ſhaddowed his intent,</l>
               <l>With ſome conceipt, ſo I the ſame way went.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thomas Parkin Chyrurgie</hi> profeſſor.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe happy ſacred hand, of our dread Soueraigne Queen,</l>
               <l>The Princely louing zeale, of her moſt Royall heart,</l>
               <l>Throughout her highnes land, her ſubiects al haue ſeen</l>
               <l>To cure, to helpe, to heale, our care, our harme, our ſmart.</l>
               <l>To God all glory for her Gratious Raigne,</l>
               <l>To her all bleſſings, that on earth remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thankes, and thankes to <hi>Clowes,</hi> for this his zealous toyle,</l>
               <l>In ſearching out the light, of <hi>Chyrons</hi> hidden skill:</l>
               <l>And for the loue he ſhewes, to Countryes natiue ſoyle,</l>
               <l>To practiſe, finde, and write, for all inſtructions ſtill,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Clowes</hi> be loued, his fame and him defend,</l>
               <l>Who, what he prooued, the ſame for vs hath pend.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:5284:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> practitioner of Phiſicke</hi> and Chyrurgery.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LET him giue thankes, that hath not elſe</l>
               <l>wherewith to gratifie</l>
               <l>His friend, that giues ſo great a gift</l>
               <l>to cure the <hi>Strumacye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor that alone he comprehends;</l>
               <l>his helpfull remedyes:</l>
               <l>Diſſolue hard <hi>Tumors,</hi> colde <hi>Inflations,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fluxes</hi> and <hi>Nodoſities:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Approaching age makes wiſdome in his tongue,</l>
               <l>His heart gain'd Arte, when yet his yeeres were young.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He <hi>Chimicke</hi> Arte diſclaimes to know,</l>
               <l>yet <hi>Ladanum</hi> he ſhowes:</l>
               <l>And many good collections more,</l>
               <l>(his pen doth heere diſcloſe)</l>
               <l>The quinteſſence of his whole life,</l>
               <l>in gayning skyll conſumed:</l>
               <l>He graunteth franckly to thine vſe,</l>
               <l>with Science ſweets perfumed.</l>
               <l>Future times ſhall praiſe his meditation,</l>
               <l>And him repoſe in Heauens conſolation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Baſe ignoraunce bids me conceale,</l>
               <l>mine owne vnworthynes:</l>
               <l>True loue to Arte compelles me more,</l>
               <l>Teſchewe vngratefulnes.</l>
               <l>Impute my faults t'affectionsforce,</l>
               <l>and his well deſeruing,</l>
               <l>That ſpends his ſprites and reſtleſſe houres,</l>
               <l>in mans life preſeruing.</l>
               <l>The long experience and good Arte of this our <hi>Clowes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſerueth rightly more reward then Lawrell bowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:5284:5"/>
               <head>AN <hi>INTRODUCTION, With an Apologie or anſwere to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> malicious back-byters.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is certainly affirmed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently reputed and holden, of diuers worthy Phiſitians and Chirurgians, both Ancient and ſuch as haue floriſhed of late yéeres, which haue intreated of the Cure of the before named do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous Maladie: and they all by one vniforme conſent and voice, conclude and agrée, that it is a <hi>Glandulus Tumour</hi> or ſwelling, hard, knotty, and kyrnelly, hauing their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and growing, contrarie and beſides nature, and is ingendred of groſſe matter and Phlegme: And (as ſaith <hi>Iacobus Ruffus</hi>) they are moſt commonly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded within their peculiar <hi>Ciſtis,</hi> filme or ſkinne, as is <hi>Steatoma, Atheroma,</hi> and <hi>Meliceris:</hi> which aforeſaid ſkin is knowne to be engendred of a colde congealed, tough, glewiſh humour or ſubſtance of the Kirnels, whereof a ſkinne is made which compaſſeth them about: Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it I haue ſéene (and alſo it is a moſt experimented truth) that ſome kindes of theſe Phlegmaticall Abſceſſions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5284:6"/>
when they haue béen beſiedged as it were, or beſet with vehement daungerous accidents, as héereafter ſhall be declared, which in continuance of time haue bin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe they haue growne corrupted &amp; vnmooueable, or fixed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the parts adioyning: whereby after there hath bin ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration made, there hath not bin found any bladder or ſkin at all, notwithſtanding the great care &amp; diligence that then was had.</p>
               <p>This moſt miſerable infirmity (ſaith <hi>Paulus Aegine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>) doth ſcituate or ſeate it ſelf in the fore part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necke &amp; vnder the Chin: alſo on the ſides of the chéekes, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſpreadeth it ſelfe vpon the breſt, &amp; vnder the Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, &amp; Groynes, &amp; ſome be déeply lodged a far off in the ſleſh, &amp; alſo do oftentimes poſſeſſe the great Vaines and <hi>Arteryes</hi> called <hi>Carotides:</hi> And thoſe that are thus vexed &amp; ſubiect to this troubleſome Infirmity, are for the moſt part Phlegmatick perſons, greatly giuen to ouermuch Idlenes &amp; ſlouthfulnes of life, &amp; are addicted to exceſſiue and inordinate eating of groſſe &amp; Flegmaticke meates: which manifolde Malady, I haue alſo found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the Cure thereof ſtretcheth it ſelfe beyond the bounds of other ordinary ſickneſſes &amp; diſeaſes. <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Celſus</hi> likewiſe ſaith, that <hi>Scrophula</hi> is a <hi>Tumour,</hi> in the which are certaine kyrnels ingendred of matter and bloud, and doe moſt chiefly grow in the fore part of the Necke, &amp; in the Arme-pits, the Groyne, &amp; in the ſides, and hath bin found in Womens breſtes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vigo</hi> a man (for his learning and experience in this Cure, &amp; in many other great Infirmities) as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, was wonderfully graced with the good opinion and fauour of the time wherein hee liued, &amp; ſince his death greatly honoured by dyuers learned Writers, and many other men famous in Phiſicke and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery: He alſo ſayth, that <hi>Scrophula</hi> taketh the name of Scropha, which ſignifieth a Sow, that is a Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5284:6"/>
and Phlegmaticke beaſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it groweth in them by reaſon of their ouermuch eating. There be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome againe which ſay, that it is called <hi>Scrophula,</hi> eyther becauſe that Sowes which giue ſucke be ſubiect to this diſeaſe, and that is by reaſon of their gréedy eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: or elſe becauſe the Sow that giueth Milke brings foorth many young ones at once.</p>
               <p>Now héere it is to be further noted, that <hi>Vigo</hi> doth not promiſe or warrant alwaies, and to euery one a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine abſolute Cure, but doth (as I, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo haue done) aſcribe the praiſe and dignity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto Kings and Quéenes of England, and of <hi>France:</hi> In déede I haue oftentimes read, and I haue alſo béen credibly enformed by Maſter <hi>Francis Raſis,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Peter Lowe,</hi> two of the French Kinges Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians, that the French King doth alſo Cure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Strumous people, onely by laying on of his hand, and ſaying: <hi>God make thee whole, the King toucheth thee; or, The King toucheth thee, the Lord make thee whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, that this diſeaſe happeneth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes<note place="margin">Hip: Aphor. ſect. 3.</note> vnto young children, which bee ſubiect to much crudity, &amp; rawe humours by voracity: but likewiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to middle aged perſons, of a ſtronger conſtitution; and alſo vnto very olde folkes. Many therefore imitating <hi>Vigo</hi> and other of our Sages, &amp; graue learned Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, doe affirme that theſe <hi>Scrophulous Tumours</hi> bee the leſſe daungerous to be cured by the Arte of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, which is taken in the beginning of the ſicknes, ſo far foorth as it wil pleaſe Almighty God to giue a grace and bleſſing to our labours. But vndoubtedly, if it be of any long continuance, the Cure thereof may prooue very hard and difficult: yea, if it be in the bodies of yong perſons: But in olde folkes I haue obſerued very ſildome, that they do receiue any curatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfectly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5284:7"/>
by the Arte of Chirurgery. I meant, that it is then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue my learning and weake capacity to cure the ſame, if the diſeaſe bee confirmed, hauing certaine occult and hidden, hard, knotty, kyrnelly ſwellings, (being deepely lodged and placed in the fleſh) but eſpecially about <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chea Arteria,</hi> or the winde Pipe, or néer the <hi>Nerui Recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes,</hi> or amongſt the great Veynes and <hi>Arteries</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named: theſe (indéede) I holde to bee for the moſt part very daungerous to be attempted, for feare of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating or touching the ſaid principall Veſſels, eyther by inciſion or Cauſtick remedies, which often times bring with them many vnfortunate <hi>Symptomes</hi> or iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous accidents, as héereafter more at large ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               <p>Alſo, it is hard to cure a noyſome, corrupt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant vlcerous <hi>Struma,</hi> which doth many times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into incurable, Cancerous &amp; rebellious <hi>Phiſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Vlcers:</hi> Likewiſe, I hold it for a certaine truth, that the Cure is not to be attempted by the Arte of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, if a man haue it by inheritance, and ſo naturally borne from their Parents: Theſe kindes of <hi>Scropholus</hi> abceſſions doe rather preſage a Diuine and holy cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is moſt admirable to the world, that I haue ſéene and knowne performed and done by the ſacred and bleſſed hands of the Quéenes moſt Royall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, whoſe happineſſe and felicity the Lord long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
               <p>But ſith the barrenneſſe of my learning, and wit is ſuch, and that my memorie will not affoord mee, héere orderlie to ſet downe in fewe words, that which I doe conceiue and vnderſtand, touching this my determined purpoſe, for the Cure of this haynous Maladie: which, in the Pilgrimage of my practize and contemplations, I haue moſt diligentlie obſerued, not onely by mine owne ſelfe, with ſuch portion of knowledge as the Lord
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5284:7"/>
hath endued me withall: But alſo I haue béen a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and a painfull obſeruer of the labours and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of others, being men of great knowledge and ſound iudgement in the Arte: Wherefore to make héere ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, the cauſe which hath pricked mee héere forward to leaue my other affaires, and ſo to drawe me from my ordinarie practiſes and ſtudies, being more beneficiall for my maintenances, is not that I goe about héereby to impaire the credit or reputation of others, being more auncient Profeſſors. It is (the Lord God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) farre from my true meaning, they are thoſe whome I loue, honour and reuerence: Neyther doe I héer am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly goe about with the ſwéet impreſſion of fayre promiſes (greater then my abilitie is) to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, or curiouſly to ſet downe, a better and perfecter way of curing this haynous Malady (then others more learned men before me) I may not well ſay ſo. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, he hardlie may be accompted for a good Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which hath learned no more then his Captaine hath taught him: or a barrenſconce, that hath no inuentions in it: But I will confeſſe héere the onely cauſe, (why I haue enterprized, or taken vpon me to write of this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Infirmitie) is I proteſt, a token of my loue and diligence towards all young Practiſers of this noble Arte of Chirurgerie, (howſoeuer otherwiſe, a painfull and tedious trauel vnto me.) Notwithſtanding, I could in no wiſe ſatiſfie the expectation of certaine of my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained friends, but that I muſt make here a true &amp; briefe rehearſall of my owne obſeruations and knowledge, touching the cure of the foreſaid Euill, which a long time I haue practiſed. How be it, being ſorry to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter<note place="margin">An Apology to anſwere certaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull back-biters.</note> offence to any, by reaſon of publication héereof. Notwithſtanding, I haue béen crediblie enformed, and alſo it is vnto my ſelfe well knowne, there bee ſome whome I litle ſuſpected, and leſſe thought vpon, would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5284:8"/>
haue béen ſo wilfully bent, without iuſt cauſe to giue occaſion of offence, and did ſéeme as it were to repine and miſlike of this my enterpriſe: and as it were, did partly reiect my knowledge and iudgement, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Cure before named: and in the preſence of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons of good ſort, brake out with ambitious curioſity, and ſaid I was not capable of the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> of this my Subiect, and ſo wanted knowledge of my ſelfe to publiſh theſe matters, which I haue héere taken vpon mee in ſome meaſure to performe: and thus went about, not onely to diſcredit mee, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to put me to vtter ſilence, as though I had ſpent all the daies of my life in the rude woodes or wilde Forreſt of Ignorance. Which thing as it gréeued me to heare, ſo in maner it forced mee to anſwere: Let theſe men ſooth themſelues (I ſay) neuer ſo much, they are knowne to be of no ſuch déep learning nor exquiſite Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, as they would make the world beléeue: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, if it pleaſe theſe enuious men to ſpeake &amp; iudge of me with equity &amp; right: it is wel knowne to moſt men,<note place="margin">He that will vſe Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery muſt needly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the wars &amp; attend on forrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Hipo. Lib. de. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</note> that I haue ſtudied &amp; practiſed this worthy Arte of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, ſithence the 4. yeare of her Maieſties Raigne, <hi>Anno Dom. 1563.</hi> Where, firſt I ſerued in her Highnes wars at <hi>New-hauen,</hi> vnder the commaund of the Right Honorable <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwicke.</hi> Knight of the Noble Order of the Garter, then Lieuetenant of the Army &amp; Forces in thoſe parts. After w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeruice being ended &amp; before, I was appointed Chirurgian, to ſerue in her Maieſties Nauy in her ſhips Royall, &amp; alſo in other men of war: within a ſmal time after, I was imployed in the <hi>Hoſpitalles</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and there practiſed the ſaid Arte of Chirurgery for certaine yéeres, vntill I was ſent for vnto the wars in the Low Countries, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earle of Leiceſter: and further, commaunded by her Maieſty, with all ſpéed to repaire vnto the ſaid Earle,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5284:8"/>
where I continued for the ſpace of 9. Moneths: &amp; ſince &amp; before I haue had conference, &amp; alſo often practiſed, with the beſt and ſkilfulleſt Chyrurgians, both Engliſh and Strangers, within the City of <hi>London</hi> and elſe where: and now as it were, partly ouer-worne with yeares and Seruices. Nothwithſtanding, by her Maieſties fauour and good liking (whome the Almighty long preſerue) now I am ſworne &amp; admitted one of her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Chirurgians. And therefore in all reaſonable<note place="margin">He that pitch doth touch, ſhall defiled be with ſuch</note> likely-hood, I am not ſo barren or groſſe witted, and vnlearned in the Arte, as ſome haue termed mee to bee. And yée ſhall further vnderſtand, it was not long before, it pleaſed ſome of them to ſay, they had graced me with the good opinion they had of me: and moreouer ſtood in the gap of my defence againſt other ſuch, which then were alſo ſore troubled with the Fluxe of a fowle mouth, &amp; vſed me at their pleaſures for their common Table talke, with ſcoffing, fléering, and deriding aboue manners and modeſty. The ſame being tolde mee, me thought it was a ſtrange alteration: howbeit, I did take their good ſpéeches very kindly, and ſo would haue done ſtill, if it had pleaſed them to continue in the ſame good opinion of me, or to haue bin ſilent. But it is truly ſaid, <hi>Hanibal</hi> knew wel how to ſubdue the <hi>Romanes,</hi> yet he knew not how to entertaine his Victories. It is not enough for a man to haue begun a good worke, vnleſſe he ſtil preſeuer &amp; continue in the ſame: Wherfore I wil héere abreuiate my ſpéeches, wiſhing to God, that this my labor were ſo perfect, that I néeded not to regard the curious examination &amp; cenſure of any aduerſary: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I detaine you with many moe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but here acknowledge my own vnworthynes. And therfore I beſéech thée friendly Reader, in a word to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer mee with pacience to ſignifie vnto you, that I doe not héere peremptorily goe about to teach or inſtruct
<pb facs="tcp:5284:9"/>
ſuch perſons which are already grounded in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and knowledge of this Arte: But my onely mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to direct my whole courſe, according (as I haue obſerued) the beſt learned haue héeretofore done in all times and ages, that is vnto the Iunior or yonger Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgiens: whe, as it were, haue made but an entrance into the practice of the ſaid facultie, whoſe ſkill (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture) is as yet not ſo profound, that they are able to ſearch or obtaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge out of ſtrange tongues, ſo farre fourth that they cannot poſſibly in a ſhort time come to the higheſt of that knowledge, which they har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely wiſh for. Indéede, it is (I ſuppoſe) vnpoſſible in the whole courſe of mans life, euen vnto that <hi>Period,</hi> which (of the Learned) is called <hi>Mans Age:</hi> that hee is able without great care, ſtudy and much diligence, to labour commendably, and with a good conſcience to worke in the Vineyard of Chyrurgery: yet I know there be many young Students in the Arte, will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready, and moſt willing to diſcharge their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes in ſuch matters as they ſhall take vpon them to deale in, whether it be in this kind of cure, or otherwiſe. And alſo will be very carefull, not onely for conſcience ſake, but euen by a naturall deſire, to ſéeke to increaſe their ſkill and neceſſary knowledge, and therefore it is truely ſaid: the good intent of ſuch honeſt and well meaning perſons, requireth a fauourable acceptation, which is as well to be eſtéemed, as the performance of them that be beſt able. And theſe will bee ready to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the ſame by yéelding ſome fruite of their painfull labour and diligence: And now I wil leaue off diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and begin to ſpeake of my determined purpoſe, and to make the ſame more plainely knowne, which I haue héertofore kept ſecret vnto my ſelfe: howbeit, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſecret that is, may no longer be called a Secret, when the whole multitude is made acquainted with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5284:9"/>
THe Cure of the foreſaid Euill is manyfolde: to wit, inwardly and out wardly, and is performed by two ſpeciall remedies: the one <hi>Medicinall,</hi> and the other <hi>Inſtrumentall,</hi> without the which fewe good workes or Cures in Chyrurgery can be brought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: The reaſon is, becauſe in this Cure, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe of the body is ſuch, which féedes the matter of the diſeaſe. Therefore, firſt of all the matter muſt be purged, for as it is ſaid, the roote of al the Cure is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wel purging of the body, whereby Nature is the better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to expell and vnburden her ſelfe of many had and vnprofitable humours. And now (by the fauour of the learned) I will therefore begin with remedies <hi>Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> according to the maner of Method, publiſhed by <hi>Calmatheus,</hi> one whome amongſt many other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in Phiſicke and Chirurgery, I haue obſerued moſt diligently, as it were a Day-ſtarre or Chriſtallin cleare looking glaſſe, following him with feruent zeale and earneſt deſire: by reaſon (as it ſéemeth vnto me) he was not ignorant in any thing that might make for the truth of his writing, chiefly for the Cure of the foreſaid Euill. Yet (I proteſt) I am no ſuch deuote fauorite of his, or any other mans whatſoeuer, further then iuſtly they haue deſerued: which is the onely cauſe that hath mooued mée to haue a reuerent eſtimation of him and all other learned men, whether they doe remaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, or otherwiſe abide with vs at home.</p>
               <p>NOw followeth the maner of Methode, by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall<note place="margin">Struma.</note> remedies for the Cure of <hi>Struma,</hi> or the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill which our Kings or Nuéenes haue and doe ſtill Cure: the experimentall proofe thereof I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times ſéene effected: wherefore I will be ſhort, and preſently procéede vnto the firſt intention.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <div n="1" type="intention_physical">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5284:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Intention Phiſicall by</hi> Inward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt Intention (after <hi>Calmatheus</hi>) in the 12. Chap. of his book, for the general cure of <hi>Vnnaturall Tumours,</hi> is that the curing of this diſeaſe called <hi>Struma,</hi> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in Dyet that dryeth moderately, &amp; heateth and attenuateth the humours: Hunger is profitable, and fulnes is hurtfull: Sléep and Idlenes are euill: exerciſe before meate very good: the vſe of <hi>Sulphure</hi> or Alume water, is very good and profitable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="intention_physical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond Intention Phiſicall</hi> by Inward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Intention is the vſe of breaking, atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating, mundifying &amp; opening Medicaments; as are theſe Remedies now following. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Recipe.</cell>
                           <cell>Rad, Ireos.</cell>
                           <cell>Cort. Sambucj.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Boiled in white wine, then adde vnto this decoction, a quantity of Ginger. For this decoction breaketh, atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth, openeth &amp; mundifieth dolorous <hi>Tumors:</hi> ſo doth it alſo prouoke vrine, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this affect is a ſpecial matter.</p>
                  <p>The often vſe of the Pilles of <hi>Hiera ſimplex</hi> is much commended to caſt out Flegme of the ſtomacke &amp; guts.</p>
                  <p>But if ſo be that thou wilt purge the whole body, thou ſhalt vſe the Pilles of <hi>Agarico Coccis:</hi> if thou liſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue &amp; caſt out Phlegme, theſe Pils following muſt be taken, viz. <hi>Pillulae de Sagap: de Opopan, de Elleboro, de Euphorbio.</hi> The Phiſitians in times paſt commended the powder of <hi>Turbith, Ginger,</hi> and <hi>Suger,</hi> of each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts: The <hi>Doſes</hi> whereof was to two <hi>Dragmes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="intention_physical">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5284:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third Intention Phiſicall</hi> by Inward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe third Intention is the vſe of this powder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which doth conſume (as they terme it) the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent matter, which it doth aſwell by his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt quality, and (as they ſay) by a ſecret property.</p>
                  <p>This powder doth conſume Phlegme, by little &amp; little.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Rad. Ariſto. Rotundae.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Raphani.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Spattulae foetidae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Fol.</cell>
                           <cell>Pimpinell.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Piloſell.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Rutae Maioris.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Scrophulariae.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Philipend.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Semen Aniſi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Zingiber.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Turbith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Optimi</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Sene Orient.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Saccari Albiſsimi.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Make all theſe into powder, and let the Patient take euery day in the morning a Spoonefull, with white Wine, or the water of Broome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Guido</hi> taketh the forenamed powders, and boyleth them in white Wine vntill halfe, &amp; giueth euery third day one quarter thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Galen</hi> approoueth &amp; commendeth the vſe of <hi>Theriaca Vetus, Athanaſia et Ambroſia.</hi> The vſe of <hi>Aurea Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drina</hi> for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomack, is very good. Alſo it is ſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5284:11"/>
that <hi>Theriaca Athanaſia</hi> doe both reſolue, breake and digeſt humours, being compact and gathered together in the profundity of the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercurialis</hi> ſaith moreouer, that about the purging of children (which is diligently to be obſerued) the ſtate of<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rging of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after Mercurialis.</note> children is weake, that it muſt bee handled with verie gentle medicines, &amp; rather to be often repeated, &amp; more eaſier then to miniſter any ſtronge Medicines: therfore the belly ſhall thus be mollifyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Mellis Roſatj. ℥. iii.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">Miſce.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Decoctionis fructuum. ℥. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Foliorum Senae. ℥. ii. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that the humours may be prepared, it muſt bee done with this Medicine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Folior. Scrophulariae</cell>
                           <cell rows="4">Ana. M. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Plantaginis.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Betonicae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Menthae.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Make a Decoction according to Arte, and then take of the ſaid Decoction <hi>℥. j. Syrupj Roſatj recentis, Oxymel. ſimpliſis Ana. ℥. ſs.</hi> Mingle theſe: When the humours bee prepared, they may be purged with this Medicine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Agaricj Trochiſcat. ℥. j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Squinantj. gra. ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Stéep them in Betony water and ſtraine them and put thereto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Mellis Roſatj ſolutiuj.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Electuarii de Pſylio.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Decoctionis Cordialis</cell>
                           <cell>℥. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Polipodio.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>Thus much as concerning this briefe note, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Methode of the forenamed Authors, which may very well ſerue for a very fit Preſident or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5284:11"/>
to the reſt that followeth:</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Now it remaineth that I make heere alſo report of the ſingular and rare efficacy of our manuel operation therunto annexed and belonging, with the right vſe of the topicall or outward remedies, which is to be externally applyed. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe it is referred vnto the ſkilfull Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans manuell or handy working, for the Cure of this great Infirmity, which doth outwardly affect the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall parts of the body.</p>
               <p>For (as ſaith <hi>Iacobus Ruffus</hi>) that to the perfection and accompliſhing of the foreſaid Cure (called, <hi>The Euill by the King,</hi> or <hi>Queene Cured</hi>) he doth reduce it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſixe Intentions Chirurgicall, as followeth. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall verifying of his excellent ſkill in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, as alſo in many others, is by diuers worthy men often times commended: which Malady doth vexe and trouble moſt pitifully the common ſort of people.<note place="margin">Iacobus Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus his 6 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgicall, by outward meanes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>1 The firſt Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Attritione, et Compreſſione.</item>
                     <label>2 The ſecond Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Diſcuſſione, et Reſolutione.</item>
                     <label>3 The third Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Suppuratione et Maturatione.</item>
                     <label>4 The fourth Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Inciſione et Extractione.</item>
                     <label>5 The fift Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Corroſione et Mundificatione.</item>
                     <label>6 The ſixt Intention is,</label>
                     <item>In Obligatione et Evultione.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>ALſo (after <hi>Fuchſius</hi> and other learned men) it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to be vnderſtood as followeth: who alſo hath written of theſe Phiegmaticall or Glandulous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions called <hi>Struma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:5284:12"/>If (ſay they) theſe abſceſſions that bee ſeated in the ſtronge parts of the body, and becauſe they are not yet olde and inueterate, hauing a thin <hi>Cyſtis</hi> that couereth them: theſe are to be appeaſed and conſumed, and after dryed vp.</p>
               <div n="1" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Intention Chyrurgicall by</hi> outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow I will ſet downe Examples and Inſtances for the Cure of the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, the which I haue obſerued and gathered (as heereafter enſueth) for the perfection and accompliſhing of the before named firſt Intention, if the ſtrength and ability of the Patient will ſerue and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſame. Then one chiefe thing (as you are before tolde) is, that the Patient doe kéep athin &amp; ſparing dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, which is the efficient cauſe belonging vnto Phiſick. The reaſon is, as I haue noted, that thoſe which are thus affected, haue alwaies a great inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a groſſe diſordered liberty of féeding: Therefore the Patient muſt be ſuſtained with ſuch meates, as are agréeable to Nature, and to eſchew ſuch meates which make groſſe Juyce: and not (as it is ſaid) to lay gorge vpon gorge. And further yée ſhall note, though it bee ſaid before, that abſtinence is greatly to be commended: yet you muſt conſider it is not meant, that Nature ſhould there by bee enféebled, or ouerthrowne, and that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in weake bodyes, great care muſt be had: But onely to kéepe all poſſible abſtinence, that is to eate and drinke ſparingly and meaſurably, onely to preſerue the ſtrength, and to ſatiſfie Nature: I meane, that it bee ſuch as is agréeable to the ſtrength of the Patient, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5284:12"/>
greatnes of the Infirmity.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe it is ſaid, the often vſe of purging and blée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on both the Armes, is profitable. Alſo, it is auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to vſe Frictions, Rubbings, Boxings, and Bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterings is much praiſed after purgings, for it ſtoppeth the flowing matter (being applyed vpon the head) by revulſion or drawing back, &amp; cauſeth euacuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, it is ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to diſcuſſe theſe kinds of <hi>Tumours</hi> which are found in mooueable parts, &amp; ſuperficially lodged néer vnto the outward parts, A plate of Leade is moſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar therfore, eſpecially in young perſons, by reaſon of the raritye and ſoftnes of the ſkinne: It is thought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit (by diuers learned men) to bliſter Childrens heads with <hi>Cantharides,</hi> it hath béen ſéene to cauſe much paine<note place="margin">Mercurialis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnetia this courſe, rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending Flamula lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, or ſuch like.</note> and piſſing of bloud: but to doe it by aduiſement, either with Muſtard or with Nettles, is good.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, many learned men, of a certaine knowledge and ſound vnderſtanding, haue in their bookes greatly commended a playſter made thus: <hi>Recipe.</hi> Olde dryed Goates dung, Hony and Vineger, being decocted at an eaſie fire, to the conſiſtence of a playſter. Alſo, Doues dung mingled with Hony, hath the ſame effect. So is it by me alſo wel approoued, this plaiſter called <hi>Oxicro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceum,</hi> whoſe compoſition is not far to be ſought for.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>℞.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Cerae, Picis, Colophen, Croci. An. ℥. iiii.</item>
                        <item>Terebinth, Galbanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ammoniaci. An. ℥. j <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. iiij.</item>
                        <item>Maſtici, Olibanum.  An. ℥. j <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. iiij.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Diſſolue the Gums in Vineger, and powder that which is to be powdred, &amp; ſo make a plaiſter according to Arte: Alſo a plaiſter of Figs baked and ſpred, and ſo applyed vpon <hi>Struma</hi> is approoued good.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, <hi>Oleum Cucumiris Aſininus,</hi> dropped into the eare, on that ſide where the Struma is, is moſt effectuall to diſperſe and diſſolue.</p>
                  <p>In like maner, is generally commended <hi>Emplaſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:13"/>
                     <hi>Ranis cum Mercurio,</hi> to be appropriate and reſpectiue in this Cure, to conſume ſuperfluous humidity, engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring this diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, vpon a time a certaine repyning enuious man, being full gorged with a malicious rayling ſpirit, being proudely giuen (in the gall of much bitterneſſe, with many ſcandalous words, and bragging compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ill beſéeming his perſon) reported that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid plaiſter <hi>De Ranis</hi> was dangerous vnto the patient; and ſaid, who ſo did holde the contrary opinion, it was<note place="margin">Such is the impudency of bolde blindnes.</note> erroneous, fooliſh and deceiptfull: by reaſon (quoth hée) of the coldnes of the Quick-ſiluer: and boldly did ſeeme to maintaine the ſame, with a number of very ſpruſe termes, and picked phraſes, like as young Children vſe to doe, when (in mockery) they counterfeite a ſtrange kinde of language, &amp; forſooth placed them as it were in <hi>Geometrical</hi> proportions, as though he had bin the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son of <hi>Archime</hi> des that great <hi>Geometritian.</hi> In déed it is a moſt true ſaying: <hi>That fiſh which is bred in the durt will alwaies taſte of the Mud:</hi> And I told him that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet found any more coldnes in this Playſter, then there is heate in a paynted fire. But this I doe ſpeake vpon mine owne knowledge, that there is as much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Arte and Judgement, betwéene this odde fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low (which would ſéeme to bee a ſecond <hi>Aeſculapius</hi>) and a man repleniſhed with true knowledge indéed, as is betwéene a Maſter Cooke and a Scullian of a Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin. Howbeit, hee ſaid alſo, that his ſkill was ſuch, that if a man were wounded at <hi>Yorke,</hi> bring him the weapon that hurt the Patient, and he would cure him (forſooth) by onely dreſſing of the weapon, and though be neuer ſée the Patient. As certaine as the Sea burnes. And now héere I will ſurceaſe to ſpeake any further of theſe matters, for I regarded not ſuch ſayings, ſith it is truely ſaid; <hi>Euery man muſt yeeld an accompt, both of</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:13"/>
                     <hi>his caſe, and of his labour. Themiſtocl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> a Captaine of<note place="margin">Scientia no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> habet inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum niſi ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norantem.</note> the <hi>Grecians</hi> (as Hiſtorians make mention) ſuppoſed it better to be en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yed of the malicious, then to liue in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlenes and baſenes of minde, without doing ſome good for the benefit of his Country and Common wealth, wherein he was borne and bred.</p>
                  <trailer>Now to the ſecond Intention, and ſo in order with the reſt as they doe lye, and offer themſelues vnto vs.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond Intention Chyrurgicall</hi> by outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Intention Chirurgicall, is the right vſe of thoſe remedies which doe mollifye, diſcuſſe and conſume great abſceſſions, which are not yet hard and inueterate.</p>
                  <p>And that the ſame is true, may eaſily be gathered as followeth. And for that I wold haue this ſecond Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made plaine (as much as in me lyeth) and alſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly knowne vnto the ſtudyous Reader: I doe therfore ſay, It is meete and conuenient, that thoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamentes which are to bee vſed, be of the Nature and property to molifie and diſcuſſe, and ſo to open the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſkinne by euaporating, breathing and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering abroad, and make thinne the groſſe matter and Phlegme. Then for the better performance thereof, without further diſcourſing, I will héere preſently ſet downe (as it were) a Store-houſe of diuers and ſundry<note place="margin">Montanus ſuppoſeth theſe Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from Melancholy</note> approoued Chirurgicall remedyes, neceſſary for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſafe healing of the forenamed <hi>Strumacie</hi> and <hi>Phlegmaticall</hi> ſickneſſe: The which from time to time I haue by experience (the Miſtris of all Aries and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) carefully obſerued, and faithfully alſo collected out of the famous writinges of ſundry worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<pb facs="tcp:5284:14"/>
as alſo out of the fruitefull labours, of diuers men famous in experience: whoſe painful trauailes and ſtudyes, haue (at this day) moſt excellently refined this worthy Arte of Chyrurgerie from <hi>Barbariſme:</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is greatly to be feared, a number at this day had not béen ſo ſkilfull and rich in knowledge, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as they are ſaid to be. Therefore we ought not to thinke any ſtudy, paines, or trauaile too great, wherein we hope of much benefit to our patients, and alſo profit and commodity to our ſelues: And héere I muſt néeds ſay, (according to my poore ability) I haue my ſelf béen very induſtrious for the common benefit, and good of others, truly to ſet downe diuers approoued remedies of mine own collection: wherin (to my knowledge) I haue not in al this whole diſcourſe, publiſhed any ſuperfluous and vnapprooued remedies, or otherwiſe kept backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy ſecret I had: but as did the <hi>Euangelicall</hi> and heauenly woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mentioned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented into the Lords Treaſury al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wealth &amp; ſubſtance ſhe had. Notwithſtanding, I haue read y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men in times paſt did with great care &amp; diligence conſecrate &amp; kéep ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret (as a precious treaſure vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) al ſuch cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen &amp; peculiar remedies, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had experienced &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued for the curing &amp; healing of any dangerous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady: and (as it is ſaid) bound themſelues by oath one to another, not to bewray their Secrets by their bookes or writings. Howbeit, I more regarding the publick vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity &amp; good of poſterity, did w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great care &amp; diligence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with my ſelf, what profit can there be to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bury his labors in the lake of obliuion, or otherwiſe to hide it in the denne of darkeneſſe. And although I know the matter héer ſpoken of, may ſéeme a paradox to ſome, &amp; ſo of ſmal worth: neuertheleſſe, although I am none of the greateſt Clarks, yet I know it wil be more auailable, then ſome happily doe make account of. For which cauſe I haue laboured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as much perſpicuity &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5284:14"/>
plainnes, as poſſible I could, to deliuet the truth of my honeſt &amp; faithful good meaning, ſo far foorth as God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> enabled me in knowledge, ſkil &amp; memory. Wherefore I meane héere preſently to make publicke &amp; open teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſame, though now and then I make a little digreſſion, and ſwarue from my matter, by reaſon of certaine Croſbyters, who haue héertofore (behinde my backe, and to my face alſo) not a little abuſed me: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, I wil héere conclude this diſcourſe concerning this <hi>Second Intention Chirurgicall,</hi> &amp; doe confeſſe and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately affirme, that there is but few mens labors at the firſt made ſo perfect, but that in proceſſe of time &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration, they may be bettered, corrected and amended. Yet I cannot but much maruaile, that wiſe men now a daies are growne to this paſſe, that they do ſo ſeriouſly follow exorciſmes and the Illuſions of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Charmes of Clowtes and Rags, which is very inhumane and barbarous; neuer practiſed, neither writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of, nor allowed by any learned Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian that euer I yet heard or read of. Howbeit, the world is (as it were) led in a ſtringe &amp; carried away to beléeue theſe vanities, which make a ſhadow or ſhew of verity for the ſafe curing of diuers maladies, &amp; ſildome (they ſay) miſſe not: But I know the contrary is true, for I haue cured both old &amp; young perſons, when theſe Charmers of clowtes &amp; rags, with their incredible ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations haue failed them, &amp; prooued flat foolery &amp; abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But to leaue this new Leach craft, with their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting inuentions, I wil here ſpeake of diuers remedies very reſpectiue &amp; appropriate, for the cure of the before named infirmity, as a preſident and example for young practizers of Chirurgery to follow. Now vnto the ſaid <hi>Second Intention,</hi> which is firſt to ſet downe thoſe ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al remedies, whoſe properties are to open the pooers of the ſkin, &amp; to ſoften the hard parts by inſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cible tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:15"/>A choyſe and ſpeciall mollyfying and reſoluing plaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſerueth well for the curing of this gréeuance: As my ſelfe haue many times approoued.<note place="margin">Iacobus Ruffus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>℞.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Serapini. ℥ iiii.</item>
                        <item>Ammoniaci. ℥ iii.</item>
                        <item>Bdeilij. ℥ i.</item>
                        <item>Galbani. ℥ i.</item>
                        <item>Euphorbij. ℥ ii.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let theſe be diſſolued in good Malmeſey, and then adde thereunto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ol. Lilior.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ol. Amigdalar.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Propoleos.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiii. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſe, fiat Implaſtrum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Clowes.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Galbani.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. ℥ iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ammoniaci.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Picis Albae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cerae Citrinae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ol. pedis Vaccini.</cell>
                           <cell>q. s.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce.</p>
                  <p>I doe many times inſtéed of the Dyle, take the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: Then what profit doth enſue, time will approue the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Haly the Abbot.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>℞.</label>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Farinae fabar.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥. v.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Farinae Hord.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5284:15"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Liqueritiae,</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> x<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Rad. Althaeae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Picis.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Cerae Albae.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥ x.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Adipis Anſerini.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let there be added the Vrine of a Boy, and of olde Oyle q s. And ſo boyle it to the forme of a Plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Baniſter.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Gum. Ammoniaci.</cell>
                           <cell>lb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſſ.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Rad. Brioniae in pul.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Turp. Mineralis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cinnabrij.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ x.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cerae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the Gumme <hi>Armoniacke</hi> bee diſſolued in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, according to Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter made vp in rowles. Among a number of his memorable déedes, which hee hath left vnto the minde and memory of poſterity, this his Plaiſter deſerueth great commendations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Mercurialis.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercurialis</hi> commendeth a Playſter made of <hi>Lyme</hi> and <hi>Salt-Petre,</hi> of each like much, being mixed with <hi>Barrowes greace. q. s.</hi> But ſuch remedyes are too ſtronge for Children, leaſt it cauſe Agnes, and hurt the ſoft and tender fleſh of their bodies, (chiefly about the Necke) it is to be auoyded. Moreouer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I read<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that to make a Playſter of <hi>Nitrum</hi> and <hi>Lyme,</hi> of each a like quantity, and of <hi>Cardamonium</hi> &amp; <hi>Fenygreeke 4.</hi> times ſo to much, and with Hony make héeroof a Plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:16"/>
                     <hi>Aetius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſaith, when <hi>Struma</hi> beginneth in children, they muſt be molifyed and diſperſed: And for mollifying in children is approoued this remedy following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Diachylon.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Oeſypi.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Radicum Ireos</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">℥ iiii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Pulueriſet.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Recipe.</label> The Lées of white or red wine, &amp; of ſtronge Vineger, of each a quart: Mallowe leaues 4. good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: Boile them till the leaues bee tender, then ſtampe the leaues, &amp; put them againe into the ſaid licour, with halfe a pound of ſwéet butter: of barley meale &amp; of beane meale, of each a good handfull: Of Linſéede &amp; Fenigrek of each 4. ounces: Of the powder of red Roſe leaues one good handfull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of yolkes of Egges 3. or 4. an of Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron the waight of 3. d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>fiat cat ap laſ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I might eaſily bring in a confuſed number of other remedies to the ſame end &amp; purpoſe, out of diuers learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mens writings, which héer to repeate were néedles, and to no great vſe, ſith I know theſe may ſuffice: Wherefore I thinke it good to pretermit the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the reſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third Intention Chyrurgicall</hi> by outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe third Intention is, to ripen, open and clenſe ſuch <hi>Phlegmaticall</hi> Corruptions and Vlcerous Apoſtumes, which do pertaine to Suppuration: This néedeth no long diſcourſe, ſith it plainely appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb facs="tcp:5284:16"/>
that theſe troubleſome, hard kernelly ſwellings, be found ſo rebellious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they doe reſiſt all emollientes and <hi>Diaphoreticall</hi> remedies before named: by meanes wherof it can not be diſſolued &amp; conſumed as we happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would, or do deſire. For which cauſes we are further conſtrained to alter our courſe, with due conſideration, that is to wit: Not to leaue the Patient helples, but to vſe ſtronger Medicamentes, I meane <hi>Suppuratiues,</hi> as is before ſaid, ſuch as whoſe property is to bring ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous humours to maturity and ripenes, by theſe and ſuch like Emplaſticke remedies, which (as it is ſaid) doe by the cloſing of the pooers of the ſkin, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the naturall heate, whereby the matter ſo enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed cauſeth the generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of matter or Pus. But I muſt confeſſe, I haue not often times ſéene theſe hard Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall abceſſions eaſily brought to ſuppuration. The matter being once colde, dull, Clammy, hard and knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and déeply ſeated, and of a long continuance in a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whoſe ſkin is groſſe and thicke, &amp; the matter hardly compact: Theſe kindes (I haue found) do ſildome come to maturity and ripenes, vnleſſe (as <hi>Cornelius Celſus</hi> ſaith) the ſaid <hi>Tumours</hi> bee mixed and made of matter and bloud. And <hi>Trincauel</hi> reporteth, that ſome of theſe<note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
                     <hi>Tumours</hi> that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eate in them, doe ripen and come to matter &amp; ſuppuration: But there be others that be more hard, and doe reſiſt ſuppuration, and then they come néerer vnto the nature of a <hi>Scirrhus.</hi> Now it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that I ſet downe thoſe approoued remedies, being in vulgar vſe, ſeruing for ſuppuration, which are long agoe ratifyed and well allowed of, by a vniforme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, both of olde &amp; late writers, which were men of an induſtrious capacity, &amp; of a moſt rare &amp; exquiſite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Arte. And firſt I wil begin with <hi>Iohannes de Vigo,</hi> one of the chief Fathers, &amp; true Patrones of al good learning &amp; knowledge in the Arte of Chirurgery:
<pb facs="tcp:5284:17"/>
As it (in ſome ſort) may appeare by Maſter <hi>Bartholmew Traheron,</hi> which firſt Tranſlated. <hi>Vigo</hi> in the Engliſh tongue. In his Epiſtle Dedicatory (whoſe iudgement therein I doe acknowledge) hee ſayth: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
                     <hi>Vigo</hi> were not brought vp in the knowledge of the Tongues, yet through his ſingular wit, long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and diligent ſtudy, hee hath inuented and ſet foorth, more notable things in the Arte of Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then any other héeretofore: and I thinke ſayth he, nothing can better teſtifye the cunning of this man, then that he continued ſo long in <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of pocky Curtezans: neither Prieſts, Biſhops, nor Cardinals excepted, as it appeareth in his Booke: for where ſuch cariones béen, the beſt Egles will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A Maturatiue Playſter.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Vigö.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Radices Althaeae.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">Ana. lb. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Capit. Liliorum.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let theſe boyle in a ſufficient quantity of Water, and after being ſtamped, put vnto them of Garlicke and white Onions roaſted, vnder the coales of each. ℥ iij.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ol. Liliorum.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Butyri.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pinguedinis porcini.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥. ii. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Anſerinae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Farinae Tritici.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. q. s.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Fenigreci.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Make a Playſter at the fire, adding in the ende, the yolkes of two Egges: There bee ſome (I know) do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:17"/>
little prize or value this Playſter, but I doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be an infallible remedy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another.</label>
                     <note place="margin">D. F.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Radices Bryoniae.</cell>
                           <cell>lb. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ceparum.</cell>
                           <cell>No. ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Rad. Althaeae recentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. iiii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Fol. Maluarum ſiccarum.</cell>
                           <cell>p. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Hidropiperis.</cell>
                           <cell>M. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ficuum.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Paſſularum Enucleatarum.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Boyle them well, then adde vnto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Fermenti.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. ℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Axungiae ſuillae Inſulſae.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Euphorbij. pul.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce et fiat Emplaſtrum ſecundum artem.</p>
                  <p>This playſter worketh miraculous effectes in this Cure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Another Playſter.</label>
                     <note place="margin">Paulus Aegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neta.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Mirrhae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ x.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ammoniaci Thymiamatis.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ vii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Viſci Quercini.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ viii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Galbani.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Propolis.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce et fiat Emplaſtrum ſecundum Artem.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A Maturatiue Cataplaſme.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Recipe.</label> Rye-bread lib. i. White Onions &amp; of Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:5284:18"/>
Rootes, roaſted vnder the Aſhes, of each <hi>4. Ounces.</hi> A Bryony Roote, and Figges boyled in Malmeſey, of each 6. Ounc. Fenygreke &amp; Lynſéede, of each 3. Oun. Barlye meale and Beane meale, of each 4. Oun. Oyle of Roſes, Camomill and Wormewood, of each 3. Oun. Hony 4. Oun. The yolkes of 4. Egges hard roaſted. Saffron the waight of 4. d. Boyle all theſe together to a laudable conſiſtence, and apply it thicke vnto the grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued partes, morning and euening warme.</p>
                  <p>Alſo I read in <hi>Iohannes Libaulty,</hi> his Booke Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">This medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialis allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth likewiſe. cap. de Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</note> 
                     <hi>Le Meſon Ruſtick,</hi> and alſo in other Learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that the dung of a Cow heated vnder the Aſhes, betwixt Vine or Colwort leaues, &amp; mingled with vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, hath the property to bring <hi>Scrophulous</hi> ſwellings to ripenes, &amp;c. Nothwithſtanding, if all theſe chaunce to faile, then haue recourſe to that which followeth in the <hi>Fourth Intention,</hi> which is perfomed by <hi>Section</hi> or <hi>Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> when wee finde the matter before rehearſed, vnfit to yéeld eyther to Reſolution or Suppuration, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourth Intention Chyrurgicall</hi> by outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe fourth Intention of theſe <hi>Strumous Tumors,</hi> which are not cured by former remedies (&amp; yet are gentle, obedient and tractable) is to cut them off, and then to pull them out.</p>
                  <p>In the vſe of theſe outward inciſions, this ſcope ought chiefly to be regarded, that is: to be very circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in your handy operations, attempted &amp; done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the cure of this great Malady: That is, the aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or opening by launcing or Inciſion of thoſe glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous <hi>Tumors.</hi> For as it is ſaid, bloud is the treaſure of life, and habitation of the ſoule: Moreouer, it is ſurely very hard and difficult, eſpecially when there is in the affected place, eyther <hi>Nerue,</hi> great Vaine, or <hi>Artery,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:5284:18"/>
Therefore ſuch perſons as are to endure this painfull action, ought to haue much patience, and to be of a good courage: Then it may bee the better attempted and done by a cunning and ſkilfull Chyrurgian: which there is no doubt, but he will be ſo prouident, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall offend. How beſt, it is not neceſſary or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable ouer curiouſly to ſearch and attempt the cutting them out by Inciſion: For that many of them are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to violent and inordinate bloudy Fluxes, and other euill accidents, which doubtleſſe will much amaze you and hinder your handy operation: I meane, when theſe <hi>Tumors</hi> bee désply planted, and ſecretly lodged amongſt the great vaines and Arteries called <hi>Carotides,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe néere the <hi>Nerui recurrentes,</hi> which is often times the cauſe that ſome bee come ſpéechleſſe there by. And it cannot be iuſtly denyed, but that theſe Inciſions haue often times béen attempted with a launce by our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors &amp; Fore-fathers. But amongſt a number of thoſe worthy men, <hi>Wickar</hi> being a man of good knowledge &amp; ſkill in the Cure of the foreſaid Euill, his counſaile is, that before we doe attempt the ſaid action by Inſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Patient be firſt layde vpon his Bed, and ſo both his féet muſt be ſtrongly iyed vnto the bed poaſts, his head &amp; both his hands muſt alſo be faſt held by men of ſtrength, and ſkilfull in holding: In ſuch ſort as we doe in cutting thoſe which haue the crooked or wrye neckes. And he that is choſen to be the Operator of the ſaid action, muſt prudently and wiſely (ſaith <hi>Vigo,</hi> and other learned men) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the greatnes &amp; ſmalnes of the ſaid <hi>Tumor,</hi> which muſt be inciſed &amp; cut fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one length of the Tumor to an other. Then by litle &amp; litle, ſeperate, diuide &amp; vndermine the whole <hi>Ciſtis</hi> round about, to the very bottome &amp; roots therof, not raſhly, nor by violence, but orderly by degrées, ſeperate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your fingers, &amp; other ſeruiceable inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as you vſe to diuide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forenamed
<pb facs="tcp:5284:19"/>
Wennes called <hi>Steatoma, Atheroma</hi> and <hi>Meliceris:</hi> And confeſſed it is for a certa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, that if any portion or part of the ſaid <hi>Ciſtis</hi> or bagge, chaunce to remaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, and not cléere taken away by the rootes, it will (doubtleſſe) bréed and increaſe againe: But to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſuch gréeuances, me thinkes I cannot ſpeake too ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly therof: wherfore, if any part remain behinde, then lay vpon it the powder of <hi>Mercury precipitate,</hi> or (if that bee too weake) adde to it of <hi>Alumen Combuſt,</hi> or <hi>Vitriolum Album combuſt,</hi> of each equall portions: notwithſtanding I beléeue, &amp; confidently hold, that the worke of your hands is the beſt inſtruments you haue to truſt to, and to relieue you in this diſtreſſe.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, <hi>Mercurialis</hi> he further ſayth theſe words,<note place="margin">Mercurialis.</note> for the curing and effecting of this matter: Firſt (ſaith he) chooſe ſome light place, &amp; let the Patient lye on his bed, for in ſitting he wil ſoone ſound: therfore binde his legges together, and after binde them to the Bedſide, and let one holde his head faſt, and then the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean taking the ſwelling in his left hand, let him make an Inciſion, eyther right or ſtraight, or ſomewhat croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, on the necke vnder the Jaw-bones, vntill he come to the matter incloſed in the Bladder, which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one and ſingle, as in the leſſer ſwellinges, and ſometimes double, like the Mirtle leafe in the greater ſwellinges: So that conueniently (eyther by the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or other Inſtrumentes) the Bladder may bee by little and little ſeparated, and drawne from the next partes, together with the matter incloſed in it. But take good héede that the Bladder be not cut, becauſe it is hardly drawne away, and much hindreth the Cure, and the euill will come againe: But if any ſuch thing chaunce, it were good to conſume it with eating Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. Great care muſt alſo be had, that neyther the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, vaines, nor notable Nerues be hurt, but by little
<pb facs="tcp:5284:19"/>
and little gently put it aſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet it in the cutting ſome veſſell be diuided, and the iſſue of bloud trouble and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worke: then apply ſome méete thing to ſtay the bloud, and ſo come againe to your worke: For if the lippes of the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſion he inflamed, and the ſwelling or <hi>Stru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a</hi> bee not ſafely diſſolued away: then lay on a <hi>Stupa</hi> beaten with the White of an Egge, and ſuch things as be good for ſtopping of bloud. After, apply Medicines that wil a little concoct, and then vſe abſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues, and next ſuch as cauſeth fleſhe to growe and heale vp the ſcarre.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fifth Intention Chyrurgicall</hi> by outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe fifth Intention is, thoſe which are vnmooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and déepely rooted within, Corrode them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and clenſe them throughly. I graunt it tollerable and very conuenient, to vſe in this Cure the due applycation of Potential Cauteries, ſuch as whoſe propertye and ſeruice is to corrode the fleſh &amp; the ſkin, and may with very good circumſpection very ſafely be attempted, being adminiſtred vpon a body that is of a reaſonable conſtitution, &amp; in ſuch ſort that his ſtrength is able to holde and endure the ſame. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>re I will make further demonſtration thereof, that is toſay: that your Cautery benot applyed vpon any Sinnewy part, neither vpon the great Vaines nor Arteries, for that theſe bee accompted indéede principall and chiefe veſſels: Alſo you muſt conſider the quallity and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the Cauſticke you doe adminiſter, for that ſome are more violent and ſtronger then other, and ſome wil run and ſpread more then another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iaques Guill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mean</hi> Chyrurgian vnto the now French
<pb facs="tcp:5284:20"/>
King which now is: ſaith, truely it is not neceſſary, nor allowable to apply the Cauſtick vpon the endes or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of Muſcles, for if your Patient that is to bee Cauterized, haue an vnſound and ſickly body, you muſt firſt of all bee ſure before you adminiſter the ſayd Cautery, to Phlebotomize &amp; purge him: The reaſon is, leaſt in the Cauterized parts, there chaunce to come concurſion, or gathering together of humours. Alſo, it is further ſayd, that a ſmall part of your potentiall Cauteryes, doth and will worke as forcibly on a ſoft and tender bodye, as a great quantity thereof will doe vpon a ſtronge and groſſe obdurate perſon. Ouer and beſides, the greater abceſſions are to bee Cauterized one way, and the leſſer an other way, and that with good conſideration. And héere to put you in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that you muſt bee very carefull and circumſpect in defending the partes round about the ſayd <hi>Tumors,</hi> for feare (as I haue ſaid) that your Cautery doe run and ſpread too farre abroad: for the which cauſe you ſhall ſtrengthen, fortifye &amp; defend the foreſaid affected parts, that is to ſay: by inuironing and compaſſing it round about with ſome repercuſſiue Medicamentes, leſt the grieued part (which by long infirmity is become there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſore weakned &amp; enféebled) and may ſo bring with it great ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>g &amp; other euill accidents: And therfore it is not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>od cauſe, that the parts gréeued be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordred &amp; defended, whereby you ſhall be ſure the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to effect your intended purpoſe without the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill or daunger but with the higheſt commendation in preuenting the euil that otherwiſe might enſue: which reaſons alwaies enduced mee to laye round about the Cauterized parts, ſome ſpeciall defenſiue, as is this, or the like héereafter following.<note place="margin">A good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſatiue.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reci. Emplaſtrum Diachalcithios</hi> diſſolued in <hi>Ol. papaueris et Ol. roſ.</hi> wherunto is added <hi>Ouorum albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:20"/>
                     <hi>et Aceti. roſ. An. q.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Et fiat Emplaſtrum.</p>
                  <p>This done, then preſently goe about with your Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke, to roote out all the whole <hi>Schrophulous</hi> and hard kernelly ſubſtances, either with the common Kuptory or Cauſticke, which in this caſe beſt contenteth my minde: the making héereof I doe not héere ſet downe, becauſe it is ſo commonly knowne.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, there is an other Cauſticke, which (as it is reported vnto me by a ſkilful Chirurgian) doth work without any paine, or very litle at al. The reputed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor therof is ſaid to bee a famous practizer in Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, dwelling at <hi>Mountpelier</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> I muſt néedes thinke reuerently of the Author of this Cauſtick, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his minde was not ſuch to delight himſelfe with publiſhing of vntruth: But if it doe indéede worke without paine, the miſtery thereof is farre aboue my reach.<note place="margin">A good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery:</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Rec.</cell>
                           <cell>Lixiuij Saponarij.</cell>
                           <cell>lib ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Vitriolj Romanj.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Mercurij ſublimatj.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Made into very fine powder: in the end of the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling put in of <hi>Opium 2.</hi> drams. <hi>Miſce et fiat Trochiſcj.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſhall further note, that if at any time your Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke doe happen not to worke ſo well and ſufficiently to your minde, as happily you would wiſh it ſhould do, then apply the ſame Cautery againe: but you muſt firſt make Inciſion alongſt wiſe, vpon the middle of the foreſaid <hi>Eſcharre:</hi> Then put in ſome ſmall quantity (that is, ſo much as you ſuppoſe will penetrate into the profundity &amp; very rootes therof) for it doth behooue a prouident &amp; wiſe Artiſt to preuent &amp; ſée all eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doing therof, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Gods help, ye may ſafely in a ſhort time roote out theſe hard <hi>Strophulous Tumors.</hi> For (as I haue ſaid) vnleſſe the roote be cleane take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:21"/>
this Malady will growe and increaſe againe. But if there chaunce to approach any painefull accidentes (as I haue knowne and ſeene to follow in ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) then with ſpéed remooue and take away the ſame: which done, yée ſhall procure the fall of the <hi>Eſchar,</hi> with <hi>Vnguentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Populeum:</hi> or els with <hi>Vnguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Roſarum,</hi> or ſwéete Butter. And to apply vpon it <hi>Emplaſtrum Diacalcitheos,</hi> or <hi>Emplaſtrum Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio.</hi> So after all the <hi>Eſcharres</hi> be remooued, then if there be required mundifying and clenſing, theſe following are vulgarly vſed, as <hi>Vnguentum Apoſtoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> called of ſome alſo <hi>Vnguentum Chriſtianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> which <hi>Vnguent</hi> in this effect cannot be bettered: and <hi>Vnguentum Egiptia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> and ſometimes to mixe two parts of <hi>Vnguentum Apoſtolorum,</hi> and one part of <hi>Vnguentum Egiptiacum.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Vnguentum Apij,</hi> is auaileable in this Cure, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vnguentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex Apio.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Recipe.</cell>
                           <cell>Succi Apijet Plantaginis.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Farinae hordej et Orobj.</cell>
                           <cell>An ℥ j. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Terebinthinae,</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Mellis,</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Mirrhae</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce et fiat Vnguentum.</p>
                  <p>If you adde to this <hi>Vnguent</hi> the yolkes of Egges and <hi>Mercury Praecipit.</hi> it doth worke much better. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the powder of <hi>Mercury praecipit.</hi> is good of it ſelfe, and if you will haue it worke more forcibly, adde vnto it of Allum <hi>combuſt</hi> according to diſcretion. With theſe foreſaid remedyes you may continue vntill there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare pure and quicke fleſh: then it followeth to vſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnatiues, &amp; Agglutinatiues, with other medicamte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, fit for conſolidation.</p>
                  <trailer>Thus hauing ſufficiently intreated of the fifth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: now it remaineth for a full concluſion, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:5284:21"/>
in order laſt of all, the ſixt Intention, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="intention_chirurgical">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſixth Intention Chyrurgicall</hi> by outward meanes.</head>
                  <p>THe ſixt Intention Chirurgicall is, that in thoſe <hi>Strumas</hi> that are faſtened but to a thinne and flen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der roote, you ſhall binde them about and plucke them out. This laſt action (as it appeareth) is verie eaſily performed by a ſkilfull Operator or cunning Chirurgian: neyther doth it require any great curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, but a decent and artificiall ſtrong binding, méete for the plucking of them out (as it is ſaid) by the rootes. In which action you néede not feare any great perrill of Fluxe of bloud, but that it may eaſily bee reſtrained with my reſtringent powder, publiſhed in my laſt booke of Obſeruations, which hath (of a number of good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes) a friendlye acceptation: If it chaunce through the ill diſpoſition of the body, any dolorous accidentes doe happen to follow, then mitigate the ſame (ſayth <hi>Wicker</hi>) with ſtupes wet in the white of an Egge, and oyle of Roſes: and afterwards if there growe filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, let it be clenſed with thoſe remedyes before rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: then no fault being committed through negligence or want of ſkill, you ſhall no doubt with good ſucceſſe, finiſh this laſt Intention. But amongſt a number of excellent remedyes for the curing of this euill (after the partes bee throughly clenſed from all annoyances) this Playſter following hath all the properties, that is preſcribed in theſe kindes of remedyes before named: Which noble Playſter I obtained of one <hi>Iſack</hi> a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger borne, a famous Inciſioner and Licentiate Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian of <hi>London,</hi> who for his excellent knowledge in
<pb facs="tcp:5284:22"/>
his Arte, was called beyond the Seas, <hi>The golden Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or Doctor.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">M. Iſackes Playſter.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Bdellii, et Ammoniaci.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ i. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Lapidis Sanguinalis, lapidis Magnetis.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ i. ſs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ariſtolochiae rotundae, aloes Hepaticae.</cell>
                           <cell>An. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Olibanj et Maſticis.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Lithargirij arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. et lapidis calaminaris.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Corallj Rubjet albi.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Lumbricorum in pul.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Succj ſcrophulariae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ vj.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Colophoniae.</cell>
                           <cell>lb ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Terebynthiae Venetae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cerae Albae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ xii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Olej Hiſpanicj.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. ℥. iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Olej Hipericj cum gummis.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Olej Laurini</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Camphor.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce et fiat Implaſtrum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>With this Playſter onely I cured a Bricklayers Daughter néere London, of diuers bad <hi>Scrophulous</hi> Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in her necke and throate. Howbeit, there be ſome (who are as it were ſo noſe-wiſe) that forſooth they can not abide to read any medicine, that is of a long com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, be it neuer ſo precious. Contrariwiſe, there be others againe, that will not endure to read a ſhort compoſition, bee it neuer ſo well approoued: for they plainely ſay, there can bee no great matter of worth in them: And thus they are as variable in their opinions (for want of true Arte and iudgement) as the Cameli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be in their colours. <hi>Quot capita tot ſenſus:</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heades ſo many opinions. Now héere I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare
<pb facs="tcp:5284:22"/>
any further to diſcourſe of this Sixt Intention Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgicall, but I will ſet downe certaine Obſeruations for the Cure of this gréeuous Malady by me perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as followeth: leaſt otherwiſe happily it may bee ſaid, <hi>He that telleth a long proceſſe or boaſting tedious tale without ſome proofe, muſt needs require credit, either for his long boaſting tedioustale, or elſe for ſome ſpeciall Authority that is in his perſon.</hi> But as for boaſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt wiſe men, it can winne litle credit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="case_study">
                  <head>An obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Few monthes paſt there was ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me by a Gentleman of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine huſband man, being about the Age of thirty yéeres, who was moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (for the ſpace of ſixe monthes) with certaine outward ſwellings, or vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>Strumous</hi> Abſceſſions: ſome of them were great with notable hardneſſes, ſome meane, and ſome ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, being for the moſt part packed and heaped together, but yet mooued too and fro, hyther and thyther: For the which he was firſt purged (with great moderation and aduiſement) with the pilles of <hi>Euphorbium</hi> and <hi>Trochiſce ex Viperis:</hi> or the Pilles of <hi>Vipers,</hi> and he did take many times <hi>Theriaca Andromachj,</hi> &amp; kept a very ſlender dyet withall: after hee was well purged from groſſe and rawe humours, then I applyed vpon his necke and both his ſhoulders 3 great cupping glaſſes, and ſo did draw bloud and humours in good quantity. After the application of this kinde of Boxing or <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſes,</hi> then preſently I applyed vpon his ſwelling this <hi>Vnguent,</hi> and theſe Plaiſters following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5284:23"/>
                     <hi>Recip.</hi> Colewort leaues, gréene Léekes and blades: of water Betonye, Motherwort, the leſſe Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,<note place="margin">The vngue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſingular good to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume all ſcrophulous Abſceſſions.</note> Dayſie leaues and Flowers, Maltows, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotian, and Pelitory of the wall, of each a handfull: Beate and ſhred theſe hearbes very fine: then adde to theſe foreſaid hearbes of Wine Vineger <hi>lib. ii.</hi> of Hogs greaſe and ſwéet Butter, of each <hi>lib. ii.</hi> of oyle of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds <hi>lib. j.</hi> a yong Fox, of earth worms, &amp; ſhel ſnailes, of each <hi>lib. i.</hi> Let all theſe lye infuſed &amp; buryed in horſe dung the ſpace of a month, then boyle all together till the watrynes be conſumed: then ſtrayne it ſtrongly, &amp; héerewith morning and euening anoynt his necke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warme, for halfe an houre together: Then applyed I <hi>Emplaſtrum de ranis cum Mercurio:</hi> and at other times, <hi>Emplaſtrum Dyachilon maius, et de Muſcilagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> of each equal portions: and by this way and order of curing, he was by me cured and ſafely healed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of 40. dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <head>Another obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a Maſter of a Ship.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon a time there was brought vnto me a certaine Maſter of a Ship, by a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of mine, called <hi>Robert Coulter,</hi> a man who (for his knowledge and ſkill in the Arte of Chirurgery) was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtéemed of diuers Nobles, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons. This Maſter of the Ship was mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infected with many <hi>Vlcerous Strumaes</hi> in his necke, throate and breſt, with much out-growing fleſh, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and vnpleaſant to beholde: his hard ſwelling ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded in number, magnitude and greatneſſe: he had a craſie and vnſound body: his minde much troubled with penſiueneſſe and melancholy fanſies. Therfore being loath to admit any thing néedfull, or commit any
<pb facs="tcp:5284:23"/>
thing hurtfull, I did take the aduiſe and counſaile of a graue and learned Phiſitian: who prepared and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his body from much crude and rawe indigeſted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementall humours, with the Pilles of <hi>Sagapenum de Agarico Coctiae. An <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. ſs. Miſce.</hi> In like manner he did ſet him downe a good regiment of dyet, which was thinne and ſparing and light of digeſtion. He alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad him eating and drinking at vnaccuſtomed houres: alſo he did refraine thoſe meates that were groſſe and tough: as Béefe, Milke, fryed Egges, hard chéeſe, all pulſe and nuttes, and other meates which cauſe thicke Juyce: Alſo he did appoint him after his firſt purgings euery morning and euening for a ſpace, to receiue this drinke following, which procured him to auoyde much Phlegmaticke rawe humours, eſpecially by Vrine.<note place="margin">A drinke to procure V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Apij Ruſticj et Eupatorij.</cell>
                           <cell>An. M. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Soldanellae.</cell>
                           <cell>M. ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Petroſelini Macedonici.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. M. j. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Herbae Trinitatis.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Mellis com. lib. ſs. Gingiberis.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Vini Albi et Aquae com.</cell>
                           <cell>An. lib. vi.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>And of fine</hi> Mythridat.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>. iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>But be ſure yée gather the hearbes when the Sunne is on them, and boyle them to the conſumption of the third part, in an earthen pot nealled and cloſe couered, ſo that no ayre goe foorth: when it is colde, ſtraine it and kéepe it in cleane veſſels.</p>
                  <p>And for that this my Patient was ſubiect to much Reſtriction of his belly: hee did alſo admit him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the foreſaid drinke, and to drink of this Laxatiue decoction a quarter of a pinte at a time, which he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued firſt in the morning, &amp; at 3. or 4. of the clocke in the
<pb facs="tcp:5284:24"/>
afternoone, and laſt in the euening.<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging decoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Sarſaeparillae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iiij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Rad. ſaſſafras.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ligni ſancti.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Epithymi.</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">An. ℥i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Hermodactil et</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Stechados,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Seminis Aniſi.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.<note place="margin">M. L.</note>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Liqueriſiae.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Senae Orientall.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Saccari albi.</cell>
                           <cell>lib. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Mithridati.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Vini albi.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">An. lib. viii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Aquae com.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Boyle them vnto the third part, and laſt put in your <hi>Senae</hi> and <hi>Mithridate,</hi> and let it not boyle much aboue halfe a dozen walmes. <hi>Et fiat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Local reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</note>Now for that his Vlcers were many, and ſubiect to a botte diſtemper, for that cauſe hee might the better admitte bloud letting, being alſo a man of a growne age, therefore I tooke the more quantity thereof. Then next I proceeded with the Cure of the before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named malignant Vlcers, and did firſt bathe or waſhe them for a good ſpace with <hi>Hydromel</hi> (that is, Well-water and Hony boyled together) by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the hotte diſtemperature, and did ſubdue the whole <hi>Scrophula,</hi> following <hi>Vigoes</hi> direction: after Inciſion I did put againe of the Cauſticke into the middle of the Carnoſity, which deceiued me not, and ſo after cauſed him to auoyde much noyſome matter and
<pb facs="tcp:5284:24"/>
filthines: Then after I did mundifye them with <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Apoſtolorum Meſuei,</hi> and of <hi>Vnguentum Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptiacum An.</hi> Oun. 2. <hi>Oleum Ouorum, Mel Roſarum An.</hi> Oun. 2. <hi>Lapis Calaminaris preparat</hi> made into moſt ſubtill powder. <hi>Miſce et fiat Vnguentum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I found this aforeſaid <hi>Vnguent</hi> very commodious and profitable in this Cure, and did continue with it till I perceiued pure and quicke fleſh: then I did alſo conſtitute and ordaine theſe two remedyes which in their operation for the cure of the ſaid <hi>Struma,</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued profitable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Recipe. </cell>
                           <cell>Saccari Plumbj.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Ol. Ouorum lutorum.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce.</p>
                  <p>This place will not admit me héere orderly, to ſet downe at large, thoſe great cures which I haue ſéene healed by other Chirurgians, of whome I obtained the knowledge of the foreſaid remedyes: And I haue alſo with the ſame, cured and healed many of the like cures, but eſpecially in the curing of fraudule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Vlcers in <hi>Ano.</hi> the ſaid remedy being Artificially made and prepared according to the Chymiſtes Arte, the ſubiect is onely <hi>Plumbj rub. et Acetj fort.</hi> Alſo I haue thought it good to ſet downe the manner of making the foreſaid <hi>Ol. Ouor.</hi> that is: take 20. or 30. Egges, more or leſſe, &amp; let them be ſodden very hard: which done, lay a ſide the whites, and reſerue onely the yolks, ſo let them be wel laboured and beaten in a cleane morter: then put them into a Frying pan, &amp; cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be well fryed, continually ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, till it come to an Oylye ſubſtance, and after preſſe it foorth according to Arte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:5284:25"/>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Recipe.</cell>
                           <cell>White Varniſh.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Lytarge of golde.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Put the Varniſh in a litle broad earthen Pan, being made flat and well nealed, the bignes of a great Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and ſtrewe in the <hi>Litarge</hi> by little and little, and ſtir it together euery two houres, and it will in the end come to a certaine hardneſſe, in ſuch ſort that you may beate it to powder, and ſtrew of this powder vpon your Pledgets, for the cure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward Abſceſſion, which likewiſe troubled him greatly, being ſo hard, nody and knotty, ſo that I feared they would haue degenerate into a <hi>Scirrhus,</hi> but I did mollify and diſſolue them with theſe remedyes following.<note place="margin">A ſpeciall molifying &amp; diſſoluing Cataplaſma</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">G. Kebble.</note>
                     <label>Recipe.</label> Turnips and Lilly rootes <hi>An. lib ſs.</hi> boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſtronge Ale or Malmeſey, <hi>q. s.</hi> which being boyled very tender, then ſtraine gently foorth the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, and beate the roote very well in a ſtone morter, and adde therunto Beane meale and Barly meale, and Ote-meale, of each a handfull: then take the liquors that the fore named rootes were boyled in, and adde thereunto Marſh Mallow rootes two handfuls, of Fenygreke and Lineſéede, each of them a handfull. Let theſe ſtand infuſed 12. houres, then boyle it to a thickneſſe, and ſo ſtraine it ſtrongly. Then take of this Muſſilage <hi>lib. ſs.</hi> and adde to it alſo Oyle of Lineſéede and ſwéet Butter <hi>An. q. s.</hi> and of Saffron the waight of 4. d. Then boyle all together to a conſiſtence. <hi>Et fiat Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taplaſma.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo, I often vſed <hi>Emplaſtrum de Ranis cum Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio et. Emplaſtrum Dyachilon maius, Emplaſtrum de Muſcilaginibus,</hi> as is before named: And thus I cured this Sea-faringman, and ſo continued (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) 11. yeares: in the end hee dyed in the laſt voyage with Sir <hi>Frances Drake.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5284:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Obſeruation of a Maide, whoſe</hi> friends ſuppoſed she had the Euill before rehearſed, when I was but a young Profeſsor in this faculty and Arte of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">An obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Maide dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at Yal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in kent</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout thirty yéeres paſt (as it were in the minority of this my practice) I did obſerue there was brought vnto me (by a Preacher, then being Vicar of <hi>Yal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> a towne in <hi>Kent</hi>) a Maiden about the age of 22. yeares, hauing a ſtronge and able body, and of a reaſonable good conſtitution, who was ſuppoſed to haue that Euill, called <hi>Struma.</hi> Yee ſhall vnderſtand, this Vicar was a man that did practiſe both Phiſicke and Chirurgery: this Mayden was a long time troubled with an Vlcer in one of her legges, and a great ſwelling in one ſide of her necke: which Maladyes, the foreſaid Vickar did take vpon him to cure and heale: how be it, in continuance of time he grew weary of his worke, and tolde a neighbour of his, called Maſter <hi>Eden</hi> (a Gentleman dwelling alſo in <hi>Yalding</hi>) that the Maide his Patient (as hee ſuppoſed) had the Quéenes Euill (which Gentlemans Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not long before I had cured of the ſame:) The ſayd Gentleman perſwaded the Vicar not to ſpend time too long, but to cauſe her to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t vp to <hi>London</hi> to mee, whoſe counſaile preſently he followed, &amp; the Vicar and the Maide and her father conſulted together, and came to mée to <hi>London,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">By the aduice of one M. Arche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boule and Beeden Chirurgians of London.</note> and ſhewed me her griefe, and the continuance of the ſame. So after diligent view taken by me, I found it was not the Euil (as he ſuppoſed) but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5284:26"/>
a ſort of crude and rawe humours, flocking together in her neck, with a putrifyed corrupt <hi>Vlcer</hi> vpon her right leg, &amp; ſo I told him he was deceiued in her griefe. Then they went their way and aſked further counſell, which all were of my opinion. Then they came vnto me the next day, and I did vndertake the cure with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of one Doctor <hi>Spering</hi> a graue and learned Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who preſcribed her an order of dyet, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient purging. It is to be noted, hee gaue vnto her in thrée ſeuerall boxes, thrée ſundry purgations to be taken at thrée ſeuerall times, ſet downe in writing very plainely, as might be deuiſed. In like maner I deliuered vnto them all ſuch locall remedies as was fit for both her griefes: amongſt the reſt I noted in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that the firſt thing ſhee ſhould vſe vnto the <hi>Vlcer</hi> on her legge, was <hi>Vnguentum Aegiptiacum,</hi> which I made very ſtrong, and of a high and thicke body, for that I would haue her ſpred it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pledgets ſomwhat thick, and after to procéede with other méete remedies.</p>
                  <p>But note what ill hap followed by the Maydes careleſnes, and too much negligence: In the morning after ſhe came home to <hi>Yalding</hi> by 7. of the clocke, and tooke one of the 3. Purgations which the Doctor gaue vnto her to take, ſhee ſet it vpon a ſtoole by the fire, where ſhee meant firſt to dreſſe her legge: in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (by great ouerſight) ſhe laide the Purgation to her legge, and did eate vp the whole boxe of <hi>Aegiptiacum,</hi> which was nere 2. oun. and (as ſhe ſaid afterwards) it was very vntoothſome and loathſome in taſting. All this while for two hours ſpace ſhe felt litle working of it, but did begin in the end greatly to burne, &amp; did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine in her ſtomacke, throate &amp; mouth, and caſted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely, &amp; alſo ſhortly after purged downe very great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; thus continued for the ſpace of one day, &amp; one night before ſhe ſought for helpe. In the end, the Vicar was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5284:26"/>
not to be found, but ſtayed at <hi>London,</hi> then they ſent vnto <hi>Maideſtone</hi> to an <hi>Italian</hi> Phiſitian called <hi>Santa-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Santa-Cilia.</note> and he being giuen to vnderſtand by them, that by meanes of a purgation, ſhee was in a great burning heate in her body, &amp; purged &amp; vomitted too aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo wanted ſléepe greatly, for the which hee gaue them a preſcript vnto the Apothecary: but firſt that they themſelues ſhould apply her with butter-milke, and new milke, and ſome good fat Mutton brothes: and to helpe to ſtay her purging, he counſailed them to giue her to drinke oftentimes, Red-wine and Conſerue of Sloes together, and to procure her to ſléepe with this potion following.<note place="margin">A potion to procure ſleep</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Diaſcordij.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> i. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Diacodij.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell cols="2">Aquae Cardui Benedicti.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>fiat potio.</p>
                  <p>But this did ſmall pleaſure. The next night hee ſent her this enſuing.<note place="margin">Another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>℞.</cell>
                           <cell>Diaſcordij.</cell>
                           <cell>℈. iiii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Philonij Romanj.</cell>
                           <cell>℈. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Aquae Cardui Benedicti.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. iii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Sir. de Succo Lymonum.</cell>
                           <cell>℥. i.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Miſce.</p>
                  <p>With this ſhe had ſome comfort, but not to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they looked for: ſo after the third night, in the next morning they ſent with all ſpéede to my houſe in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> with a letter, of the great daunger ſhe was in, &amp; the Phiſitians billes with all what ſhe had done: and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently I ſent it to D. <hi>Spering,</hi> who was greatly gréeued to heare of it, &amp; ſaid he was ſure there was ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary matter in it, for the purgations he ſent would neuer bring her into ſuch danger. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after he had well conſidered of the matter, &amp; preſent daunger that might
<pb facs="tcp:5284:27"/>
enſue, hee preſcribed foorth with that his Apothecary ſhould make firſt, for to coole and quench her great and extreame thirſt, and to helpe her to her taſting againe, this <hi>Iulip</hi> which was thus made.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rec.</hi> Barly Water <hi>lib. iiii.</hi> Conſerue of red Roſes and of Barberyes, of each 2. Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: Whereunto was added 20. droppes of Oyle of Vitrioll. <hi>Miſce.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then ſhe did drinke for a ſpace, which wrought to good effect in cooling of her, &amp; ſo brought her to a good taſte againe. For the ſtaying of the Fluxe of her Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Vomiting, ſhe tooke of this Electuary at diuers times a day, the quantity of 3. Oun. at a time. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king héereof is as followeth.<note place="margin">An Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſtay great Fluxes in the Belly.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Recipe.</cell>
                           <cell>Bol. Armoniacj Orient.</cell>
                           <cell>℥j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cynamomj.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Cloues and Nutmegs roaſted.</cell>
                           <cell>An. ℥. ſs.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Macis.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Sanguinis Hominis, <hi>dryed in the Sun, and made into fine powder.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>℥ ij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Corticis Balaſtej.</cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Of white Paper ſhred into a number of ſmall péeces: of Sorrell ſéedes, and of Plantine ſéedes, dryed and made into fine powder, of each.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>℥ j.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Boyle theſe in 12. Oun. of Sirupe of Vineger, till it come vnto the thicknes of an Electuary, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>He gaue alſo vnto her the firſt night, a Pill of Lada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, onely to procure ſléepe and quiet reſt, and cauſed her to be couered with many cloathes, and ſo procured ſweate: Thus within an houre and a quarter ſhee fell a ſléepe, and reſted quietly vntill mine of the clocke the next morning, and neuer caſted nor went to the ſtoole: and (being awaked) confeſſed ſhee was greatly refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and felt no paines at all till towards night, and then ſhee caſted a litle, and went now and then to the ſtoole:
<pb facs="tcp:5284:27"/>
for which cauſe ſhe tooke her fore ſaid Electuary. She earneſtly required to haue an other Pill, but the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor gaue his direction to the contrary, and would firſt ſée how Nature did diſpoſe her ſelfe: ſo the night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhe reſted but litle, how be it a great deale better then before. Then the third night hee gaue her the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Pill, and after that ſhe neuer vomitted or purged diſorderly againe: the excellency of theſe remedyes is aboue beliefe and vncredible, that I haue done and ſéen done by theſe laſt worthy remedyes, both by Sea and by land The ſeauenth day after ſhe had receiued her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Purgation of <hi>Aegiptiacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> then ſpéeches was made by me to ſée the Vlcer of her legge, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded it not; in the ende ſhe opened it, and found it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cleane cured, then ſhee commended mee, and ſo did her friends for this my excellent remedy: but ſhee ſaid would neuer take the like Purgation againe, for a thouſand pound: thus ſhe was cured by Fortune and not by Arte. Then I required of her, where the Boxes were, that the Purgations and the <hi>Vnguentum Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiacum</hi> were in? ſhe ſaid ſhe threwe them both into the fire: For (ſaid ſhee) the Purgation had a filthy taſte, and was ſo clammy, and ſo ſticked to her mouth and téeth, that I had neuer ſo much a doe (ſaid ſhe) to get it downe my throate. Then I perceiued ſhee had taken the wrongthing, &amp; it was the more apparant by reaſon of the blacknes of her téeth, &amp; the ſtaines of her cloathes wherwith ſhe had often wiped her mouth: and alſo by ſtaining of the Baſons and the diſhes, wherin ſhe had ſo often times vomitted. After this I ſtayed with her tendaies, til her legge and mouth was perfectly cured, and then wee were royally payde, and thus went to <hi>London</hi> to the Doctor, and tolde him what had hapned, that ſhe had eaten the boxe of <hi>Aegiptiacum,</hi> and layde the Purgation to her legge, whereat he was greatly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:
<pb facs="tcp:5284:28"/>
and much controuerſie in ſpéeches was after betwéene the Doctor and the Maides father, but in the ende they were made friends.</p>
                  <p>Now I will ſet downe the compoſition of the ſaid Pill of <hi>Ladanum,</hi> which I obtained of a very déere friend, being a pretious Jewell, as it is vſed: otherwiſe, (as I haue ſaid in other of my writings) the beſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine that is, is no Medicine vnleſſe it be in the hands of a ſkilfull man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="excursus_on_Laudanum">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The true maner and making</hi> of Ladanum.</head>
                  <p>TAke of <hi>Opium,</hi> firſt ſliced thinne and then dryed in an Earthen platter, one Oun. &amp; a halfe. of the gum of the roote of Henbane 3. Oun. Make the Gum thus. Gather the rootes of white Henbane in March (the Moone being full) and drie them in the ſhadow: after ſlice them and boyle them in good white Wine: (the rootes being boyled vntil they be very ſoft) poure off the wine, being full of the tincture therof, and preſſe ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the rootes, the licour (being by filtration clenſed from all dregs) in an earthen broad pan vpon warme aſhes: Vapour away the moyſture vntill the tincture of the Henbane rootes come to the conſiſtence of Hony, which is very ſwéet and pleaſant. After this, take all theſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten to powder) of the ſéedes of white Poppy one Ounce, of Mummia one ſcruple, of Cloues and Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, of each 2. Ounces, of Louage roots, <hi>Calamus, Arc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus, Galingale</hi> and Ginger, of each one Ounce, of <hi>Caſtorium,</hi> blacke Pepper, Cubebs and Saffron, of each halfe an Ounce, of <hi>Ladanum</hi> and <hi>Beniamin,</hi> of each 2. 3. Put all theſe together in a glaſſe hauing a narrow mouth, which will holde a pottle, and poure in ſo much good and ſtrong <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> as wil be aboue them foure
<pb facs="tcp:5284:28"/>
inches, then with a Corke and a péece of Leather ſtop it, and let it ſtand vntill the <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> be of a darke red colour, ſhaking it thrée times a day in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaſſe: the <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> being full of tincture, let it bee poured off &amp; ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo much againe be poured on, do this til the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua Vitae</hi> can draw no colour. Then take all the tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured <hi>Aqua Vitae,</hi> and in <hi>Balnea Mariae</hi> in a great glaſſe body, diſtill it vntill the tinctures doe come to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of a Syrope: Afterwardes poure them in a broad earthen glaſed pan, and on warme Aſhes by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporation bring them to the conſiſtence and body of a Pill, which Malax with 2. drams of the oyle of Cloues, let the maſſe be kept in a cleane glaſſe.</p>
                  <p>The Doſe is from thrée graines to fiue, to procure ſleepe, to aſwage the paines of thoſe that are troubled with the Collicke, with the Pluriſie, with the Stone, and with the Goute: to ſtay the Cough, the Fluxe of the Belly, ſpitting of bloud, and Defluxions of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, &amp;c. It is ſaid, it were as good for a Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that followeth the warres, eyther by Sea or Land, to bee without his right hand, as to bee without theſe remedyes laſt rehearſed. My ſelfe haue knowne cured<note place="margin">Diuers cured of Dyſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, or the bloudy Flixe and other Fluxes of the belly.</note> of <hi>Dyſenteria,</hi> or the bloudy Flix, and other Fluxes of the belly in a Shippe (being vpon the coaſte of <hi>Indyes</hi>) forty Marriners and Soldiers at one time, and not one of them all periſhed, by the diſcréet adminiſtration of the ſaid remedyes by ſeruantes of mine. Within the Citty of <hi>London</hi> alſo there be aliue at this preſent day, which were cured of the Fluxe of the belly, by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named remedyes, when they were ſuppoſed of many to be paſt all recouery, by reaſon alſo of the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and their extreame weakenes withall: And here I wiſh the like good ſucceſſe vnto others (which I my ſelfe haue had héereby) that is the onely cauſe I haue héere made ſo large mention thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5284:29"/>
                  <head>A moſt miraculous Cure, healed onely by the Queenes moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, when neither Phiſicke nor Chirurgery could take place or preuaile.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (which I haue knowne dayly cured by her Highnes, of the foreſaid euill) this cure following is worthy of great admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: there came into my handes not many yeares paſt, a certayne Stranger, borne (as he ſaid) in the Land of <hi>Gulicke</hi> neere vnto <hi>Cleaueland.</hi> This Stranger had béen in Cure a long time before he came vnto me, with diuers ſkilfull Chirurgians, both Engliſh and Strangers, being then greatly moleſted and ſore troubled with diuers perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Cancerous Fiſtulous Vicers</hi> in certaine places of his body: likewiſe he had many knotty ſwellings or abſceſſions, gathered together vpon heapes in the fore part of his necke, néere vnto the Winde-pipe, and ſome in the binder part of the necke: and alſo amongſt the principall and notable veſſels, <hi>viz.</hi> the great Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, Vaines and Arteryes, and therefore could not without great perill and danger be ſafely taken away, eyther by Launce or Cauſticke remedies, by reaſon of their néere knitting together, &amp; were alſo very vnfit, to be brought to ſuppuration. The cauſe was, they were for the moſt part ingendred of dull and ſlowe or tough
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5284:29"/>
ſlimie matter, for the which I craued now and then the aduyce and counſaſle of diuerſe learned and expert Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians and Chirurgians, onely to preuent and auoide thoſe pernitious daungers that oftentimes doe follow: Howbeit, (in concluſion) notwithſtanding all our turmoiling, much care, induſtry and diligence, with the application of moſt excellent medicines (very remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and appropriat for that cure) yet was his griefe rather the worſe then better. For looke what way ſoeuer we tooke with approoued medicines, ſome milde, ſome vehement, and ſome ſtronger (which by naturall reaſon and common ſenſe, were very good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable) yea, and which brought oftentimes all his Vlcers to bee very néere whole: Yet vpon a ſodaine (without any iuſt cauſe to vs knowne) his ſores did pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifye and breake foorth againe, with much loathſome filthineſſe, ſo that I feared his Vlcers would gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, by reaſon of the concurſion and vigour of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected accidents, ſo that his diſeaſe wearied vs all. In the end, after hee had béen twelue or thirtéene monethes in my cure, perceiuing we all miſt of our expected hope and purpoſe for the curing of this Infirmity: And likewiſe himſelf being ouertyred with extreame paines and griefe, ſo that oftentimes hee be wailed his owne great miſery and wretchednes: for which cauſe hee went his waies, and came no more vnto mee for any cure: but by the counſaile of ſome of his owne countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and friends, made meanes (vnknowne to me) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other of my fellowes the Quéenes Maieſties Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians, which are in place of preferment before mée. Who pitying his miſerable eſtate, vpon a time (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many others) he was then preſented vnto our moſt Sacred and renowmed Prince the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſty, for the cure of the ſaid Euill: which through the gift and power of Almightie God, by her
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5284:30"/>
Graces onely meanes laying of her bleſſed and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie handes vpon him, ſhee cured him ſafely within the ſpace of ſixe monthes. Heereby it appeareth it is a more diuine then humane worke, ſo afterwards vpon a time I did meete with him by chaunce in <hi>London,</hi> but I did not wel-know him, his Colour &amp; complexion was ſo greatly altered &amp; amended: And being in very comely maner attired, otherwiſe then before I had ſéene him, and he tolde me who he was: Then I aſked him how he did w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his griefe? he anſwered me, I thank God and the Queene of England, I am by her Maieſty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured and healed: and after her Grace had touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, I neuer applyed any Medicine at all, but kept it cleane, with ſwéet and freſh cleane cloathes, and nowe and then waſhed the ſore with white Wine: and thus all my griefes did conſume and waſte cleane away. And that I ſhould credit him the more, be ſhewed mée the Angell of golde which her Maieſty did put about his neck, truely a cure (as I haue ſaid) requireth diuine honour and reuerence: And héere I doe confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſtéedfaſtly beléeue, that (for the certaine cure of this moſt miſerable Malady) when all Artes and Sciences doe faile, her Highneſſe is the onely Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarre, péereleſſe and without compariſon: for whoſe long life, much happines, peace and tranquillity, let vs all (according to our bounden dutyes) continually pray vnto the Almighty God, that he will bleſſe, kéepe and defend her Sacred perſon, from the malice of all her knowne and vnknowne enemies, ſo that ſhee may for euer raigne ouer vs, (if it pleaſe the Lord God) euen vnto the ende of the world, ſtill to cure and heale many thouſands moe, then euer ſhe hath yet done.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5284:30"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An History and obſeruation of a</hi> Gentleman which ſent for me, to cure him of the foreſaid Euill, but it prooued otherwiſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon a time I was ſent for to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, lying in a Marchantes houſe at Broken-wharfe in <hi>London:</hi> after I was brought into his preſence, he did foorth with giue me to vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was greatly polluted &amp; moleſted with much impurity of corrupt &amp; rotten matter, with great exulceration in his throate, being of a filthy and carrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſauour: alſo the Almond of his throate was grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and painful vnto him, &amp; meruailouſly ſwolne: for the which cauſe (he ſaid) he entertained (a litle before) one D. <hi>Simonds,</hi> a very learned and Judiciall Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who (as he reported) did adminiſter a dyet to him for certaine daies, but it appeared he was ſmally relieued therby. And further he laide open vnto mee, that of late there was commended vnto him a New-come Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who (vpon report) was ſuppoſed to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi>
                     <note place="margin">It is truely ſaid, giue a man a name to be an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riſer though hee lye in bed till noone, it is no great matter.</note> of the world, for his rare and exquiſite knowledge in Phiſicke and Chirurgery: I anſwered the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that thoſe ſpéeches were ſo abſurd as nothing could be more, for (ſaid I) it is impoſſible for one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue all knowledge in himſelf, but it is truely ſaid: <hi>One man may know, that which another knoweth not.</hi> Well quoth he, I perceiue I haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wrong pig by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eare, and ſo haue brought my hogs to a faire market, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I know not what to ſay: &amp; I doubt me I ſhal find a wofull experience, of that he hath practiſed on me: And therfore ſaid, he I pray you let me haue your good help
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5284:31"/>
in curing of me, for preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting further danger. Indéed he is more to be eſtéemed that preuenteth a danger before it doth come, then hee that doth cure it after it is come; Wel ſaid he, the firſt time he had giuen me a litle Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, hee did very boldly corroſiue mee in two ſeuerall places of my throate, and yet neuertheleſſe I receiued no profit thereby, but hee hath tormented me greatly: So in the end he prayed me to vnbinde his grief, where the corroſiue was applyed, which was directly vpon the outward part of the Amigdales or Kernels of the roate of the tongue, but as good hap was, he being a fat man, the Cauſtick wrought not too déep: alſo he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mee diuers nodoſities, knobs and knottes vpon his ſhin bones. Then I tolde the Gentleman it was not the Kings Euil: when he heard me ſpeake theſe words, he was in a wonderfull rage, and did ſweare like a mad man. By the way yée ſhall vnderſtand, that this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans vices excéeded his vertues, hee was a man knowne to be as vnconſtant &amp; vncertaine as the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cock: won with a feather &amp; loſt with a ſtraw, today a friend, to morrow none: at one time he would mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifye his Phiſitian and Chirurgian (as it were) aboue the heauens, and for the wagging of a ruſh, hee would diſcredit them &amp; diſpraiſe them againe, downe to the pit of hell. But to returne vnto my matter, from whence I haue a litle digreſſed, forſooth in all poſte haſt this good Gentleman would néedes haue me ride into the Country to his houſe (being fifty miles from <hi>London</hi>) to cure him there: But I tolde him, it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for that I was dayly to attend vpon the Lord <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Earle of Suſſex, then being Lord Chamberlaine vnto her Maieſty. In the meane ſpace there came in his Phiſitian and Chirurgian whome he reported be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be matchleſſe, and without compariſon in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5284:31"/>
and Chirurgery: but the caſe is altered, for now he did againe, moſt bitterly reuile him, for miſtaking of his griefe: I muſt néeds ſay, his Phiſitian was a man of a curteous inclination, and partly after ſpéeches had, he did confeſſe his error and ouer-ſight: yet he ſaid hee had béen a profeſſor of this faculty forty yéeres, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed he had the teſtimonies of many great townes and Cityes beyond the Seas, of diuers whome hee had cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Kings Euill: To iudge and iudge aright,<note place="margin">Where ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is clad in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned weede, Small helpe is there to be had in time of neede.</note> (as I tolde the Gentleman) hee did nothing of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to abuſe him, for truely he was learned, though a had Phiſitian and a worſe Chirurgian. How he it, the worſt I liked in him, was for that he boaſted, and ſaid he was a Chirurgian naturalized, and ſo borne a Chirurgian: truely I tolde him it was a reaſon as naked as my naile: For be it graunted that his Father might bee a good Chirurgian (as him ſelfe reported to vs) what is that to the purpoſe, if his Sonne be found a counterfeit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is a true ſaying, the beſt Apple will growe to be a Crab, vnleſſe ſome good fruite be grafted on the ſtocke: But indéede I doe know there bee ſome whoſe Fathers were good Chirurgians, and ſo be their Sonnes likwiſe, but how commeth it to paſſe they bee ſo? Truely the reaſon is, they were like vnto their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, men carefull and painfull in ſtudy, and of long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. But otherwiſe, for any one to ſuppoſe or dreame, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Arte commeth to a man by ſucceſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe happily his Father was a good Chirurgian, it is a Paradoxicall opinion, very fooliſh, abſurde and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall: Other the like ſpéeches hee had to this ende and purpoſe, and thus we ended, and ſo I took my leaue, and left them altogether. After I was gone, they fell out with great and vnſéemely wordes: whereupon the Gentleman cauſed his men to ſet his Phiſitian downe in a Chaire, and then with a payre of Taylors ſhéeres,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5284:32"/>
one of his men played <hi>Barba tonſoris,</hi> and ſo did Cutte off his faire beard, and ſhore off the hayre of his head very vnſéemely, being a man of his yéeres, and ſo put him out of doores, without any conſideration for his paines and Medicines hee had beſtowed vpon him: but what became of him afterward I haue not heard. Then he ſent to D. <hi>Simonds</hi> againe, &amp; tolde him how his new come Phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Chirur: had abuſed him &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him of all friendſhip to help him preſently to ſome cunning Chirurgian, to cure him foorth with if it were poſſible, &amp; that with ſpéed: After ſome talke, the Doctor remembred himſelfe, and tolde him he would ſend him a neighbour of his, one Ma. <hi>Story,</hi> a Chyrurgian of S. Bartholmewes Hoſpitall, &amp; a man (ſaid he) wel ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in his Arte. After he was come home to his houſe, he did conuerſe with his neyghbour M. <hi>Story,</hi> &amp; tolde him what maner of haſty man the Gent. was: therfore he willed him, ſaying, before you meddle with him make your bargaine wiſely now he is in paine, for hee is but a bad pay-maſter, and therefore follow this rule. <hi>Accipe dum dolet, cum ſanus ſoluere noler.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As cunning as Maſter Storye thought to haue béen, hee could not get one penny out of his purſe, not in ſixe daies after hee vndertooke to cure him, vntill Maſter Story was going away, and ſaid, ſir I cannot goe to the market with wordes, but the Gentleman would not heare on that ſide. Then the Doctor went with Maſter <hi>Story,</hi> and tolde the Gentleman: <hi>Sir if you ride your horſe all day, and giue him no meate at night, and ſo againe all the next day, you may bee ſure you are like to goe a foote the third day.</hi> Indeede I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a pretty ſaying of one, whoſe wordes in effect were theſe: <hi>When a Phiſitian or a Chyrurgian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to a man that lyeth ſicke, and is in daunger of death, yet by his iudgement and skill, promiſeth with</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:5284:32"/>
                     <hi>Gods helpe, to cure him of his griefes and Maladyes: then the ſicke Patient greatly reioyceth, &amp; preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth him to a God: But after, being ſomewhat recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and perceiueth good amendment, then he doth ſay, hee is but an Angell, &amp; not a God: Againe, after hee doth walke abroad and falleth to his meate, truely he is then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted no better then a man: in the end when he happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commeth for his money for the curing of his grieuous ſicknes, he now reporteth him to be a deuill, &amp; ſo ſhut the doore; Non eſt inuentus; come when I ſend for you.</hi> To conclude, &amp; now I come againe to ſpeake of Ma. <hi>Story,</hi> after hée had béen comming and going, twice a day for eyght daies ſpace, hee gaue him certaine money, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a world of faire promiſes, ſo far foorth as he would perfect his Cure at his houſe in the countrie: But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old ſaying in Latin, <hi>Mel in ore verbalactis fel in corda fraus in factis,</hi> as by the ſequell ſhall appeare.</p>
                  <p>At much intreatie hee conſented, and went downe to his houſe in the Country: when hee came vnto the Gentlemans houſe with him, hee tolde Maſter Storie ſaying: I haue a Store-houſe of diſeaſes and impedimentes in my body, and ſo I haue not ledde a Saintes life: as hee confeſſed very ſtrange and far from all good, to this ende (he ſayd hee ſpake it) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee might bee the better inſtructed to make his cure the more certayne: Then hee tolde the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman hee would be loath to begin a thing when the ende is doubtfull and daungerous, and vnto him before altogether vnknowne: And therefore deſired him to ſend for ſome ſkilfull Phiſitian or Chirurgian, for further counſaile to his good. Then he did ſweare &amp; ſtare, that he did not bring him downe to expoſtulate and make Lectures vnto him, but he ſaid he did vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by M. D. <hi>Simondes,</hi> that he was able to performe greater cures then his was, without the counſel of any
<pb facs="tcp:5284:33"/>
other, and folde Maſter <hi>Story</hi> he ſhould not depart aliue out of his houſe, if hee did not perfectly cure him. I truſt (ſayd Maſter <hi>Story</hi>) you will not (what ſoeuer you ſay) commit ſo foule a fault in your owne houſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may follow vnto you ſuch diſhonour: Howbeit, Maſter <hi>Story</hi> was greatly troubled in minde, and ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no remedy, he endeuoured himſelfe with great care and induſtry, to attempt the ſaid Cure, according to the Gentlemans owne requeſt, which was with the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but firſt he prepared and afterwards purged his body, and opened a vaine, and after very diſcréetly hee did adminiſter the Vnction at ſeuerall times, vntill hee did ſée and perceiue it had wrought ſufficiently, and to Maſter <hi>Stories</hi> owne good liking, and ſo meant to haue ceaſed. But this monſter in humanity (contrary to all Arte and reaſon) compelled Maſter <hi>Storie</hi> to adminiſter the Vnction once againe, ſaying his body was ſtrong enough to endure it. Howbeit, within three dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he did begin to ſing a new ſong, for ſtrange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected accidents immediatly did follow: A great and an inordinate Fluxe of vicious and corrupt humours paſſed out of his mouth, with much acrimony, burning heate and ſharpnes, by reaſon of the putrifaction of his gummes, with an horrible ſtincking ſauour and a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner accompanying the ſame: Then he and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about him, were in great doubt of his recouery, ſaying to Maſter <hi>Story,</hi> my griefe (I feare me) will prooue inſanable and deadly. Maſter <hi>Story</hi> ſaid he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped not ſo, for you may thanke your ſelf of this extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Then ſecretly (doubting he ſhould dye) he ſent an olde truſtie ſeruant of his to <hi>London</hi> in all poſte haſte for me, with a Letter ſubſcribed by a wrong name, and by his man 20. Angels. After I had peruſed his letter, and vnderſtood in what a bad caſe he was, I prepared all things neceſſary, and ſo with all expedition ridde
<pb facs="tcp:5284:33"/>
poaſt away with his guide. But when I came into his houſe where he lay, I did not knowe him, his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe had ſo altered the naturall ſhape of his face: at laſt he reuealed him ſelfe vnto me, and ſaid, Maſter <hi>Clowes,</hi> I haue ſent for you, hoping you wil ſaue my life, I haue béene abuſed by counterfeit bungling botchers, for one told me I had the K. Euill, and another, I haue the <hi>Fr. P.</hi> but what ſoeuer it is, I pray you bend your ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour<note place="margin">Some ſay, It is not good to ſpeake the truth at all times.</note> and diligence, that with al conuenient ſpéed I may be brought to my former health, which I know (ſayd he) reſteth in the ſkill of a good Chirurgian. After I vnderſtood what hee was, I repented mee of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, &amp; wiſht my ſelfe at <hi>London</hi> againe, &amp; his 20. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in his belly. To procéede, I tolde him hee was not without danger, &amp; therfore I could not make any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his cure, but the beſt I could do he ſhould be ſure of: then this cankred chuffe looked on me like one that had lately come out of the deuils ſlaughter-houſe, &amp; ſaid: if he dyed vnder my cure, there were in his houſe, that ſhould take accompt of me before I went. Then I tolde him, if he or any of his durſt touch or abuſe one haire of my head, it would bee déerely anſwered. But before I procéed any further, you ſhal vnderſtand, I was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by one of the Gentlemens men, that M. <hi>Story</hi> was kept in obſcurity (&amp; as it were in a cloſe priſon.) So vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſodaine, about 10. a clock at night, this Gentle. ſent a ſwaſh buckler of his own training vp, who was vnto him (as it were) the very light of his eyes, &amp; one that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him in a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of bad matters: He came to M. <hi>Story</hi> &amp; cauſed him to riſe out of his bed, and bad him prepare to ride towardes <hi>London,</hi> for hee ſaid he had ordained horſes for himſelfe, &amp; you M. <hi>Story,</hi> &amp;c. I will ſoone bee ready to attend vpon you, ſaid hee, but firſt (he ſaid) hee would faine haue taken his leaue of the Gent: but this Royſter tolde him it was in vaine, his Maſter had no
<pb facs="tcp:5284:34"/>
pleaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght of his perſon: So they took horſe, &amp; towards <hi>London</hi> they did ride, vntill they came into a very great wood farre from any houſe or towne, and in the midſt of the wood hee forced Maſter <hi>Storie</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, with many ſcoffes and ſcornes, and being very barke, left him to ſhift for himſelfe, where hee wandred vp and downe all the night, with great feare, ſorrow and care, till it was day, &amp; then in the end he came into <hi>London</hi> hye way, and ſo being ouer-wearyed, reſted him ſelfe for a ſpace, and in the end went to his houſe in <hi>London.</hi> After, when this griſſie ghoſt (his man) came home, in the morning hee informed his good Maſter, how he had dealt with Maſter <hi>Story,</hi> whereat (though he being ſore and ſicklie) yet hee ſmiled, and greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced at this bad action: which I did heare, &amp; full wel vnderſtood though I ſaid litle, whatſoeuer I thought, but marke hereafter the end of the Maſter and the man: and now I come againe to my owne procéedings, that is. The morning after Ma. <hi>Story</hi> was gone, I admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto this Gentleman a Gliſter, made of new Milke, Suger and Oyle of Almonds, which could in no wiſe haue been lawfully prohibited, by reaſon of the great reſtriction and torments of his belly, for hee had not a ſtoole in fiue dayes before. Now I ſuppoſe ſome vpon a ſpleane, will obiect againſt me, and ſay, that I goe (here and in other places of this booke) beyond my latchet, in the publiſhing &amp; adminiſtring of phiſical re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, vnto my Patients: But I muſt craue pardon to anſwere with fauour this obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for be it without offence ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I ſay, where the learned Phiſitian is not to be had, be it either by ſea or land, far or néer, I wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe al honeſt &amp; lawful meanes, bath in Phiſicke &amp; Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, to the vttermoſt of my knowledge and ſkill, before I will any way permit and ſuffer my Patient to periſh for want of all helpe. Notwithſtanding, what
<pb facs="tcp:5284:34"/>
ſoeuer is ſaid and ſpoken to the contrarie by any mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aduerſary, I aſſure my ſelfe, the graue, wiſe and learned will not take offence at theſe my ſayings, but paſſe it ouer with modeſty &amp; ſilence, Secondly, though he were weake, by reaſon of his extreame ſweates, paines, and burning heate of his mouth, throate and whole body, for which cauſe I did let him bloud on the <hi>Caephalica</hi> vaine, on the right arme, that was, 4. Ounc. of bloud in the morning, and 3. Ounces of bloud more at foure of the clocke in the after noone the ſame day. And thus by intermiſſion of time, I took away 7. Oun. of very corrupt and impure bloud: this done, I vſed fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and I ſet ſtrong cupping glaſſes vpon his ſhoulders and hippes, and at ſundry times I did admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto him certaine comfortable cordials: And then with excellent Gargariſmes and Lotions, I brought away many foule and filthye Aſkers from his mouth and throate: thus within the ſpace of ſixe daies, hee did confeſſe ſome little eaſe and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by theſe inward and outward medicaments. And at the full end of 18. daies after following, I made him perfectly whole, in the meane time hee did cogitate (as it were) and bethought with himſelfe, how cunningly he had dealt with his two former Chyrurgians, and did greatly reioyce in this ſending them away vnſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Then I tolde him, it was to Maſter <hi>Stotyes</hi> great detriment, &amp; hurt vnto his body, and hindrance to his liuing being a poore man: but hee would not heare on that ſide. Notwithſtanding, it is a true ſaying: <hi>It is an ill winde that bloweth no man good;</hi> I meane, happy is hee that commeth in the declination and ending of a Cure: and ſo I let him alone with his humours, ſith my reaſons was not of force to perſwade him: howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, in concluſion he vſed me very kindly, &amp; willed me to goe abroad with him, to ſée his Riuers, wherein were
<pb facs="tcp:5284:35"/>
many goodly Trow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es and other fine fiſhes, and after ſhewed me his mighty high woods, and a number of Heronſhew-neſtes: But truely, I tooke as much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at the ſight thereof, as Iacke an Apes doth when he hath a whip at his tayle. After all theſe ſightes, he returned to his houſe, and by the way he ſaid, Maſter <hi>Clowes,</hi> I will holde you no longer with me, but I will ſend you with my men to <hi>London,</hi> for I muſt confeſſe I haue ſtayed you longer time then I meant to haue done: and in concluſion, he gaue me 20. pound, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed mee to reſt my aſſured good friend during his life. But to conclude, I note his vnfortunate end, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it preſaged he was borne vnder ſome vnluckie Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net or Croſſe day. For within fewe yéeres after, he took occaſion to ride abroad, as at many other times he vſed to doe, but in returning home to his owne houſe, it was ſaid, he entring into a Lane, and attempting to open a great gate, ſodainly his horſe ſtarted aſide, and fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,<note place="margin">He liued wickedly &amp; dyed miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably.</note> whereby the Gentleman fell from his horſe vnto the ground, and there ſodainly brake his owne necke: So his horſe ran home, and he being left behinde, the ſeruants went and ſought for him, and found him ſtark dead, and his necke broke: Thus far of the end of the Maſter, now to the end of his man, which he appointed to be Maſter <hi>Storyes</hi> guide, the onely <hi>Phoenix,</hi> whom to déerely loued, but not for his good conditions. Within a yéere after his Ma<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> came to his vntimely death, (whoſe end was onely to God foreknown &amp; prefixed) this ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering fellow did ſodainly grow into great miſery, &amp; ſo vpon a time hee came to <hi>London,</hi> and there I ſaw him: preſently hee craued of mee ſome reliefe, for hee ſaid; for want of ſeruice hee was brought into great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty: Indéede I muſt confeſſe I had ſmall deuotion vnto him, but yet I gaue him ſome what to be rid of his company: thus he went his waies, ſaying he did hope
<pb facs="tcp:5284:35"/>
it would be better or worſe with him ſhortly. Indéed it was reported that not long after, he did conſort with a crew of his old co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions, &amp; they together immediatly robbed certain Cloathiers of the weſt country, &amp; being al take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſſiſes hanged on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gallows at <hi>Ailes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A fit Pulpit for ſuch a Prophet.</note> or there abouts, for the ſaid fact. Thus (friendly Readers) you haue heard (as it were) the tragical hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the foreſaid Gentleman and his man. The cauſe which hath mooued mee to publiſh the ſame is, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne al young practiſers of this faculty of Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being indéed truely called <hi>filius Artis,</hi> to beware and take héede how they goe, and where and with whome they goe, eſpecially into ſtrange and vnknowne places, and vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch extraordinary &amp; ſtrange qualities, which make but a ieſt &amp; paſtime at the abuſing of any man, be he of neuer ſo much worth, honeſty &amp; ſkil in his profeſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="case_study">
                  <head>An obſeruation for the Cure of Struma, performed by me vpon a woman dwelling in the County of Eſſex. 1602.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt others that I haue cured this preſent yéere <hi>Anno 1602.</hi> there repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me, a woman being about the age of thirtye yéeres, dwelling in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> thrée miles from my now dwelling houſe at <hi>Plaſto,</hi> in the pariſh of <hi>Weſtham,</hi> within the ſaid County: which woman was a long time moleſted and troubled with certaine Carnoſityes and hard <hi>Strumous</hi> ſwellinges vnder her Chinne, ſome mooueable and ſome vnmooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: the which woman I did take in cure, for the ſaid infirmity, and after ſpéeches had, I perſwaded her
<pb facs="tcp:5284:36"/>
that ſhee would permit mee to take her <hi>Strumous</hi> ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings away by Inciſion, but it fell out ſhee ſhewed her ſelfe faint-hearted, and ſo vnwilling to ſuffer that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Inciſion. Notwithſtanding, ſhe hauing an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire and affection to bee cured by mee, was very willing to indure and abide the force and painfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Cauſticke, which was performed as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
                  <p>The incredible operation of this ſimple Cauſticke now following is aboue beliefe, being indéed made but onely of the powder of new quick burnt Lime-ſtones, as they come out of the Kyll, and of Sope well mixed together, <hi>An. q. s.</hi> Héere ſome peraduenture wil ſay, it is a great vanity in mée, to commend a remedie which is well knowne already, (it will doe that it is preſcribed for) but I will leaue to anſwere ſuch obiections, and will procéede with matter of more importance, that is to wit: After I had well defended the partes about, then I applyed vpon theſe ſwellinges, the aforeſaid Canſticke, which ſhe reaſonable well endured, for the ſpace of thrée houres: and then I remooued it, and in place thereof I applyed other medicaments, onely to mollifye and looſe the Aſkers, which was made by the ſaid Cauſticke, and alſo I gaue with her (of the ſame remedy) home to her houſe, to dreſſe her ſelfe with all: where ſhee remained for the ſpace of fiue daies, in the end yée ſhall note, ſhe returned againe to me, being very faint, pale and ill coloured, thereat I much maruail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſée ſo ſodaine an alteration: then I demaunded the reaſon of her, ſhee anſwered and ſaid it was by reaſon of the bad ſent and ill ſauours of the Aſkers, and of the filthy corrupt matter, which did run from the foreſaid Cauterized <hi>Strumous</hi> ſwellings, that greatly offended her ſtomacke, and by reaſon of the ſenſibilitie of the grieued partes, which were ſharpe, mordant and
<pb facs="tcp:5284:36"/>
byting, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and further, the confeſſed in the end, that He was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> with o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilde, which troubled her greatly, all which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes being conſidered, I very much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> an vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ely birth, but I tolde her ſhe was much to a blame, that ſhe did not acquaint me there with, before (I tooke her in cure. Howbeit, God did ſo open my knowledge and vnderſtanding, that all thinges fell happily out, better then we looked for. So after, I appointed her to bee dreſt twiſe a day with conuenient remedies, and then by the vſe of ſome metalline inſtruments, onely to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and to pull out part of the foreſaid <hi>Strumous</hi> ſwellings. So, according as I haue ſaid before, thoſe which are Maſters and Profeſſors, choſen to performe the like operation, ought indéede to haue a Lyons heart, a Ladies hand, and a Haukes eye, for that it is a worke of no ſmal importance. Then by the applyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe two noble compoſitions, being irreprooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and moſt iudicially penned, and of great truth and probability in this cure, that is <hi>Vnguentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Apoſtoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meſuae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vnguentum Aegiptiacum,</hi> with other worthy Agglutinatiues and drying medicaments, often times before named, and thus ſhe was perfectly cured within the ſpace of 10. wéeks. Friendly Reader, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe chiefly which hath mooued mee to publiſh this obſeruation amongſt the reſt, is partly (as I haue before ſaid) to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome fruites of my labours, ſtudies and time ſpent, which as it may héere appeare, is no afternoone mans worke, as ſome rake-ſhames &amp; belly Gods haue falſly and ſlaunderouſly ſo reported: but the troth is I haue carefully laboured héere, alſo to admoniſh eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry young practiſer of Chirurgery, which is rightly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>filius Artis,</hi> that hee in no wiſe attempt the like cure, vpon any woman with childe, without ſome ſage aduiſe: for great was the troubles and daungers
<pb facs="tcp:5284:37"/>
that was like to haue followed, but happily were they preuented through the helpe of Almighty God, &amp;c. Now héere I will forbeare any further to diſcourſe héerein, but I will ſet downe certaine Preſcriptions worthy of obſeruing, which I haue gathered out of Plinie, (a moſt worthy writer) for the cure of the fore named Euill, the which I wil heere ſet downe word for word, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="excursus_from_Pliny">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The cure of the King or Queenes</hi> Euill, after Plinius Secundus deſcription.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bloud of a Weizell is good for the Wennes called the King or Quéenes Euill, when they be exulcerate and doe run: ſo is the Weyſell it ſelfe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in Wine, and applyed. Prouided alwaies, that they run not by the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any launcing or Inciſion, made by the Chirurgians hand: and it is commonly ſaid, that to eate the fleſh of a Wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zell is as effectuall for the cure: ſo are the Aſhes of a Weizell calcined vpon the fire made of Vinetwigs, if they be incorporated with Hogs greaſe. Item, take a gréene Lyzard and binde it to the ſore, but (after thirtie daies) you muſt doe ſo with another, and this wil heale them. Some make no more a doe, but in a little boxe of ſiluer, kéepe the heart of a Weizell, and weare it about them. If a Woman or a Maide bee troubled with the Kings or Quéenes Euill, it were good to make a Plaiſter or Linament of old ſhell Snailes, and
<pb facs="tcp:5284:37"/>
let them be ſtamped ſhelles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>lly ſuch as be ſticking to the rootes of ſhr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>es of buſhes. The Aſhes of a Serpent <hi>Aſpis</hi> calcyned are likewiſe very good for this diſeaſe, if they be incorporated with Buls Tallow, and ſo applyed. Some vſe Snakes greaſe and Oyle together: alſo a Linament made of the aſhes of Snakes burnt, tempered with Oyle and Waxe. Moreouer, it is thought that the middle part of a Snake (after the head and tayle bee both cut away) is very wholeſome meate for thoſe that haue the Kinges Euill: or to drinke the Aſhes, being in the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner prepared, burnt in a new Earthen pot neuer occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed. Marry, if the ſaid Snakes chaunce to be killed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two Cart trackes where the whéele went, the Medicine will worke much more effectuall. Some giue counſell to apply vnto the affected place Crickets dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the earth, with the moulde and all that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp: alſo to apply Pigeons dung, onely without any thing elſe, or at the moſt tempered with Barly meale, or Ote-meale in Vineger: likewiſe, to make a Linament of Mouldwarpes aſhes, incorporate with Hony. Some there be that take the Liuer of a Moule cruſhed and bruiſed betwéene their hands, working it to a Linament, and lay the ſame to the ſore, and there let it dry vpon the place, and waſh it not in thrée dayes. And they affirme that the foote of a Moulde is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler good remedy for this diſeaſe: others catch ſome of them, and cut off their heads, ſtampe them with the moulde that they haue wrought and caſt vp aboue ground, and reduce them into certayne trocheſces, which kéepe in a boxe or potte of Tinne, and vſe them by way of applycation, to all <hi>Tumours</hi> and Impoſtumes, which the Gréekes call <hi>Apoſthemata,</hi> and eſpeciallie thoſe that ryſe in the Necke: but then they forbid the Patient to eate Porke, or any Swine,
<pb facs="tcp:5284:38"/>
during the Cure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Moreouer, there is a kinde of earth. Béetles, called <hi>Tauri</hi> or bulles, which name they took of the little Hornets that they carry, for otherwiſe in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour they reſemble Tickes, ſome terme them <hi>Pedicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los terrarum</hi> or earth Lice: theſe worke alſo vnder the ground like Wantes, and caſt vp moulde which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in a Linament for the Kings Euill, and ſuch like ſwellings: alſo for the Goute in the feete, but it muſt not be waſhed off in thrée dayes ſpace. Howbeit, this is to be noted, that the medicine muſt be renewed euery yéere, for the ſame moulde will continue no longer in vertue then one yéere: In ſome, there be attributed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Béetles, all thoſe medicinall properties which I haue aſſigned vnto Crickets called <hi>Grillj.</hi> Moreouer, ſome there be, who vſe (in maner and caſes afore ſaid) the moulde which Antes doe caſt vp. Others (for the Kinges Euill) take vp as many Maddes or Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes in number, as there be Wennes gathered and knotted together, and binde the ſame faſt vnto them, letting them dry vpon the place, and they are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the ſame Wennes will dry and conſume away together with them. There be againe, who doe get a Viper, about the riſing of the Dog-ſtarre, cutting off the head and tayle, (as I ſaid before of the Snakes) and the middle part betweene they burne: the Aſhes that come thereof, they giue afterwards to drinke for thrée wéekes together, euery day as much as may be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and taken vp at thrée fingers endes, and thus they cure the Kings Euill. Moreouer, there bee ſome which hang a Viper by a Linnen thréed, faſt tyed ſomewhat vnder the head, ſo long till ſhee be ſtrangled and dead, and with that thréed binde the Wennes or Kings Euill aforeſaid, promiſing vnto the Patient aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured remedye thereby: They vſe alſo the Sowes called <hi>Multipedae,</hi> &amp; incorporate the ſame with a fourth
<pb facs="tcp:5284:38"/>
part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be of that opinion, that this Oy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſufficient to cure an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> whatſoeuer. <hi>Aet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> alſo ſayth, if a man ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>te a Viper, it is a moſt notable thing: whoſe authority others alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in adminiſtring vnto <hi>Strumous</hi> perſons <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſcos Viperinos,</hi> or the Pilles of Vipers, with good &amp; happy ſucceſſe. Alſo it was ſaid, it was the experience in times paſt of countrymen, that if any had eaten a Snake, hee ſhould bee deliuered from <hi>Struma.</hi> Thus much touching <hi>Pliny</hi> his manner and order which hee hath publiſhed, for the Curing the Kings or Quéenes Euill.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd thus (friendly Reader) it were a great argument of folly &amp; ſhameles im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency in me, worthy to be laughed at, once to think that I could héer any way inſtruct the learned Phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, in the Cure of the Kinges or Quéenes Euill, before named. I am not ſo full of childiſh toyes: but if I were, I doe full well know they might by their prouident wiſedomes and learning eaſily circumuent mee, though I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I am not altogether inſufficient to performe this enterprize I haue héere ſet downe and taken in hand. The onely cauſe why I haue done it, is (as I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid) for the benefit of all young Students of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, who haue a long time expected the comming foorth and the publiſhing of this Booke: whoſe honeſt zeale and affection towards me, hath induced mee the rather to ſet foorth the ſame. But before I would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it without good aduiſe, I did firſt intreate diuers
<pb facs="tcp:5284:39"/>
Phiſitians and Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> uerance, in peruſing and examming the ſame) of whom I haue had a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urable acceptation: And this I did of purpoſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome might (otherwiſe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umbling blocks in my way, onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpeach theſe my painfull labors &amp; trauel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And ſo I do make a final end, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging as I did in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, <hi>That the gift of healing, is the gift of God:</hi> howbeit, I doe not héere preſume, or once take vpon me to enter into the high cure of the ſaid Euill vſually called <hi>Schrophula,</hi> in ſuch wiſe as God hath giuen diuine &amp; peculiar giftes vnto Princes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but my full intent hath alwaies been onely to direct the true path-way of Artificial gifts (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God of his great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes giueth to men of Arte) knowledge &amp; ſkil in Phiſick &amp; Chirurgery, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is performed &amp; done by the applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of interiall &amp; exteriall medicamentes, appropriate &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued profitable therfore. For it is a true ſaying: <hi>God hath created medicines of the earth,</hi> for the reliefe &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of man; and it is ſaid: <hi>He that is wiſe wil not refuſe it.</hi> And thus laſt of all, I thought it not impertinent, héer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to diuert &amp; digreſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the matter, &amp; wholy attribute all diuine honor &amp; reuerence, for the great cure of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Euill, (by Gods gratious good gifts) vnto our moſt prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wiſe &amp; vertuous Princeſſe, the Quéenes moſt Royall Maieſty: For whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s all pray, that the Lord God Almighty &amp; eternal Sauiour wil ſend her Highnes ſtil long and long to raigne ouer vs, to our great toy, happines &amp; comfort, ſo that ſhe may liue long, and many happy yéeres &amp; daies, to hold vp the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pter of this Kingdome, in Chriſt Ieſus. Amen.</p>
               <lg type="closer">
                  <l>The Lord of Hoaſtes, preſerue theſe coaſtes.</l>
                  <l>Our gratious Queene defend:</l>
                  <l>And graunt her peace may ſtill increaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vntill this world ſhall end.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
